<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Scarbroughs spagyrical anatomizer dissected, or, An answer to all that Dr. Tonstal hath objected in his book against Scarbrough spaw the innocency and excellency of that spaw is further asserted 1. Concerning the rise and growth of the art of physick, 2. Touching the causes of the petrifying property that is in some springs, and more especially that of the dropping well at Knaresbrough, 3. About the signs, symptomes and cures of diseases : as also reflections upon a late piece, called A vindication of hydrologia chymica / by Robert Wittie ...</title>
            <author>Wittie, Robert, 1613?-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1672</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 181 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 80 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A66809</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3233</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38727</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17948203</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17948203</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106770</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A66809)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106770)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1112:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Scarbroughs spagyrical anatomizer dissected, or, An answer to all that Dr. Tonstal hath objected in his book against Scarbrough spaw the innocency and excellency of that spaw is further asserted 1. Concerning the rise and growth of the art of physick, 2. Touching the causes of the petrifying property that is in some springs, and more especially that of the dropping well at Knaresbrough, 3. About the signs, symptomes and cures of diseases : as also reflections upon a late piece, called A vindication of hydrologia chymica / by Robert Wittie ...</title>
                  <author>Wittie, Robert, 1613?-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32], 127 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B.G. for Nath. Brooke ... and R. Lambert ... in York ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1672.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Tonstall, George, b. 1616 or 17. --  Scarbrough spaw spagyrically anatomized.</term>
               <term>Simpson, William, 1627?-1671. --  Hydrological essayes, or, A vindication of hydrologia chymica.</term>
               <term>Mineral waters --  England --  Scarborough.</term>
               <term>Mineral waters --  Therapeutic use --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Health resorts --  England --  Scarborough.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106770:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>SCARBRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GHS Spagyrical Anatomizer diſſected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>OR AN ANSWER To all that Dr. <hi>Tonſtal</hi> hath Objected in his Book againſt <hi>Scarbrough Spaw.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Innocency</hi> and <hi>Excellency</hi> of that Spaw is further aſſerted</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. Concerning the Riſe and Growth of the <hi>Art of Phyſick,</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. Touching the Cauſes of the <hi>Petrifying Property</hi> that is in ſome Springs, and more eſpecially that of the Dropping well at <hi>Knaresbrough.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. About the Signs, Symptomes and Cures of Diſeaſes.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>As alſo Reflections upon a late Piece, called a</hi> Vindication of Hydrologia Chymica.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Robert Wittie</hi> Doctor in Phyſick.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London.</hi> Printed by <hi>B. G.</hi> for <hi>Nath. Brooke</hi> at the An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>el in Cornhil and <hi>R. Lambert</hi> at Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-Gate in <hi>York,</hi> Anno Dom. 1672.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:106770:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:106770:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Honourable</hi> JAMES Earl of Suffolk, JOHN Lord Roos, <hi>Son and Heir to the</hi> Earl of Rutland, <hi>and</hi> JAMES Lord Anneſley, <hi>Son and Heir to the</hi> Earl of Angleſey.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Am once more ingaged to appear again in Publick, in defence of <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> which is now accuſed to be a dangerous Water; and what fitter <hi>Judges</hi> of this Controverſie can be found out then your <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> who have tried it, and found it not only moſt <hi>Innocent,</hi> but <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent.</hi> My ultimate and higheſt Appeal is therefore to your <hi>Honours,</hi> ſince two of your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> do bear its Teſtimony within you.</p>
            <p>As for you my <hi>Lord Anneſley,</hi> though I cannot ſay this laſt of your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> ſince you did not drink of it out of any neceſſity, but for company of your <hi>Noble Brother</hi> the laſt Summer: yet this I may ſay, your <hi>Lordſhip</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:106770:3"/>had an ill ſhare of it, if it have the faults that ſome have aſcribed to it. And farther, your <hi>Acute Judgment</hi> and <hi>Excellent Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> wherewith you are qualified for the <hi>Higheſt Service</hi> of your <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Country</hi> when called, renders your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> a moſt competent <hi>Judge</hi> of this Subject, beyond all Impoſition. And the Favourable Aſpect which then both your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> were pleaſed to <hi>Grace</hi> this Diſcourſe and its Author withal, do juſtly challenge this my <hi>Thankful</hi> and <hi>Publick Acknowledgment.</hi> I humbly beg of <hi>all your Lordſhips</hi> the Acceptance of this, in token of the great <hi>Service</hi> and <hi>Honour</hi> I owe you, for all your <hi>Noble Favours</hi> vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>York <date>
                     <hi>June 3. 1671.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <salute>My Lords,</salute> 
               <signed>Your <hi>Lordſhips</hi> moſt humble Servant <hi>R. WITTIE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106770:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>MEthink I hear ſome object that my Anſwer to this Book comes too late, ſo as I might have ſpared my ſelf this labour, a return being laſt Summer made thereto, in a piece called <hi>A Vindication of Hydrologia Chymica.</hi> To which I reply, <hi>Sat cito ſi bene ſat,</hi> it is ſoon enough if it be well enough. This was finiſhed in <hi>June</hi> laſt, as ſome <hi>Perſons of Honour</hi> do know, before that came out, but was thought fit to be ſuppreſt t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll the year came about, when the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters here treated of might become the common ſubject of diſcourſe. And further I ſhall ſay, if my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer be but like that, then have I loſt my labour, and thou thy mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, for in the judgement of learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:106770:4"/>men, it will (with that) deſerve nothing but to be imployed in the moſt <hi>homely uſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Author is ſcarce ſatisfied with any thing that this ſayes, ſave only where he oppoſes and girds at me. What the one calls the <hi>Glebe of Alome,</hi> the other calls the <hi>Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra of Iron.</hi> The one calls the Salt of Alome an <hi>Alkali,</hi> the other an <hi>Acid Salt.</hi> The one affirms an Aci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dity to be in Nitre, the other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies it; nor do their reaſons con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince each other. Thus it appears they do not well underſtand the Terms of the Art they profeſs; and truly when men run careers in the dark, its no wonder to have them juſtle. And though they differ, yet its pretty ſport to ſee how they claw one another with the frequent Title of <hi>Ingenious Friend,</hi> while yet I am not allowed to diſſent, be my reaſons never ſo cogent, but I am called out of my <hi>name</hi> by the young
<pb facs="tcp:106770:4"/>man with unſcholar-like reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and new invented ſtories, that have not the leaſt pretence of truth in them.</p>
            <p>The great fault they find in <hi>Scarb. Spaw,</hi> and which they reckon to be its diſparagement, is the great quantity of Mineral ſediment that remains after evaporation over the fire. I declare I never ſaw harm come from thence. The only fault I know in that Spring, is that it is placed in an angle of the Kingdom, at ſo great diſtance from <hi>London,</hi> and the midland Counties, where if providence had ordered it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing found to have the vertues both of <hi>Epſam</hi> and <hi>Tunbridge,</hi> it would have been more known, and better truſted then now it is.</p>
            <p>Now though like <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s <hi>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xes</hi> they turn tails of one another, yet they agree in this, to fire their neighbors Corn, and cauſeleſly to diſparage the Spring, revenging
<pb facs="tcp:106770:5"/>their Schiſm upon themſelves by ſeparating from one another, as they do both from the truth. And though Mr. <hi>S.</hi> can hardly cloſe with Dr. <hi>Y. S.</hi> arguments againſt the Spaw, yet out of deſign he ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſomewhat of it may be true, on purpoſe to make room for himſelf, and ſo undertakes to give rules of advice to thoſe that come there; where he ſays no more then what may ſure ſuch ſubjects in general, but wiſely refers the Patients to adviſe with thoſe that underſtand their caſes better. At laſt he proves moſt ingenious, and calls it a <hi>noble Spaw,</hi> wherewith he would im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove other Spaws, even that at <hi>Knaresbrough,</hi> (p. 152.) <hi>by diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Salts of Scarbrough water to make it more effectual.</hi> Why could not he ſay ſo before? — but however <hi>Nunquam ſera eſt, &amp;c.</hi> And 'tis honeſtly ſaid, let the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals be wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t and how many they
<pb facs="tcp:106770:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>will: of which more anon. My re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply is this in a word; <hi>Quod efficit tale, illud eſt magis tale.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I may not paſs that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of mine, the Author of the <hi>Vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Hydrol. Chymica,</hi> and his Book without a further ſurvey. That <hi>Hydrol. Chymic.</hi> is little elſe then a <hi>Rapſody of Railing</hi> firſt againſt me, about my Book of the Spaw, and then againſt the <hi>Galeniſts</hi> and their <hi>Method.</hi> To that Book I gave Anſwer, juſtifying what I had writ about the Principles of the Spaw, and at laſt after a great deal o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>bad language that he had given me for aſſiſting them, I found him <hi>recanting</hi> in his Epilogue, and confeſſing them all. I alſo maintained the Honour and Reputation of thoſe worthy Gentlemen the <hi>Galeniſis,</hi> and their <hi>method of Phyſick,</hi> (who deſerve a better Champion) both from <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and alſo the <hi>Authority</hi> of the moſt eminent among the
<pb facs="tcp:106770:6"/>
               <hi>Chymiſts,</hi> who all go that way. Nor has that Diſcourſe been unwelcome to the Nation, but I have had thanks from many <hi>private Gentlemen,</hi> both of our own Faculty and others, yea and from ſome <hi>publick Societies</hi> of Learned men. Now when I had ſo fully diſcovered his errors to him, an ingenious man would rather have repented and cried <hi>peccavi,</hi> then writ a <hi>vindication:</hi> what faults he made there, he has aggravated in this with more groſs circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He charges my quotations of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors to be impertinent, or their ſenſe to be perverted, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> their words falſly tranſlated.</hi>— This I expected he would ſay, if any thing, for he has front enough to deny the concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, where he cannot ſtand againſt the premiſes. The truth is, I was very careful in my collections of Authority, fetching every thing from the <hi>fountains</hi> and not from the
<pb facs="tcp:106770:6"/>
               <hi>ſtreams,</hi> even from the original Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors themſelves, whoſe very pages in things moſt material I uſually cited, on purpoſe to ſtop his cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour. Nor have I deſignedly wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in any one place the ſenſe of any one Author. Nor have I falſly tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated a word, or added a tittle more then what was neceſſary to preſerve the idiome of each lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage, or make the ſenſe intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gible to common Readers. I appeal to the Learned who have read my Book, who are moſt competent Judges betwixt us.</p>
            <p>Nor is it material what he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects to the contrary (<hi>p.</hi> 41.) where I citing a place out of <hi>Paracelſus</hi> concerning Minerals and Mettals imbibed in water, he ſays I added by a Parentheſis <hi>(diſſolved in wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter)</hi> I therefore did put them into a <hi>Parentheſis,</hi> becauſe they are not expreſſed in the Latin among thoſe words, but they are ſo neceſſarily
<pb facs="tcp:106770:7"/>implied, as the Authors ſenſe would be loſt if I had not expreſſed them; and the following words do plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make it out, <hi>viz. Haecenim aqua ſunt, &amp;c.</hi> (lib. 4. cap. 1. <hi>de creſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centibus Aquis</hi> p. 271.</p>
            <p>So again in the ſame page where I cite <hi>Paracelſus</hi> ſpeaking of vitriol, <hi>(id ſi in Aquam reſolva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ur colorem omnem deponit)</hi> he quarrels at the tranſlation of the word <hi>(in)</hi> which ſhould be <hi>(into)</hi> and impoſes ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely upon me for it — Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was omitted in my Copy or by the Printer, it matters nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Men of Reaſon, ſince there can be nothing gained by it: but certainly its not ſo <hi>pedantick</hi> as <hi>pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rile,</hi> and argues a deſperate ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wrack of his Cauſe, while he has no better Ancher-hold to ſtick by, then the defect of an inſignificant Particle.</p>
            <p>He tells a ſtory in his Preface, which for fureneſs of memory he
<pb facs="tcp:106770:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>repeats again in his Book, that <hi>in a debate about the Exiſtence of Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol in the Spaw, I was put to ſuch a ſtrait to defend it, that after ſome paſſion of fear, aiſcovered by a ſudden paleneſs in my face, I had no other refuge but to fly to the</hi> ipſe dixit <hi>of Dr.</hi> Tonſtal, <hi>and ſaid he told me it was Vitriol laſt year.</hi> Will any man of reaſon believe that he whom I ſo lately laſhed about in my Book, and that among others about this very thing, and catched him in nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen contradictions, beſides other abſurdities, ſhould on the ſudden become ſo formidable to me, while yet he urged nothing but what I had anſwered in my Book? And yet hence he indeavours to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade, that I had publiſhed nothing concerning that Mineral, but what I had borrowed from Dr. <hi>T.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning that debate I could ſay ſomething from the teſtimony of the Gentlemen then preſent, of
<pb facs="tcp:106770:8"/>their diſreliſh of his arguments and behavior, inſomuch as ſome of them hiſſed at him. But I ſhall only offer this at preſent, that I have been acquainted with that Spaw above thirty years, and am known to many to have always aſſerted Vitriol, upon the Reaſons menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned in my Books. And in Anno 1660. my firſt Edition of <hi>Scarb. Spaw</hi> came out, with my reaſons for that mineral among the reſt, which is now eleven years. Now Dr. <hi>Tonſtal</hi> I think never ſaw this Spring till the year 1668. when he came to me, and confeſſed himſelf a ſtranger to it, asking my advice about his Wife; then did I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince him of all the minerals in the Spring, ſo as he was ſatisfied abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly at that time, which gave me occaſion to mention his name in my Anſwer to <hi>Hyd. Chym. p.</hi> 107. So as in that debate I asked him the queſtion, what ſay you to this, in
<pb facs="tcp:106770:8"/>Anno 1669. But then his mind was changed, and the <hi>Vitriol</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come <hi>Nitre,</hi> querying alſo whether the Spaw were better if it had Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol or no; which I told him was a new ſubject, and required longer debate. Now what ground there is for this his charge, that my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal ſhould be to him, as having that notion from him, let any man of reaſon judge, and thereby take meaſure of the temper of this man, and conſequently of his cauſe which needs ſuch ſupports. I am certain I ſhall find Dr. <hi>Tonſtal</hi> juſt towards me in this point, if any man ſhall enquire of him.</p>
            <p>But he forges another figment ariſing from my fear of him about the Vitriol, when the <hi>Chymical Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thecary</hi> taking a piece of Alome-ſtone out of the vitrioline bed that is in the cliff, and putting it into water with gall, found it ſtrike a black tincture, inferring thence that
<pb facs="tcp:106770:9"/>
               <hi>the Tincture in the Water was from the Alome, and that there was no Vitriol.</hi> I anſwered, ſo would the earth in that place give a tincture, but neither earth nor the 100. loads of Alome that are in that cliff elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where would do it; here they cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured extreamly, but upon that he ſayes, <hi>that I was ſo touched to the quick, that I called the Apothecary aſide, and ſaid, if Mr.</hi> Simpſon <hi>would lay down the cudgéls, I would not only look upon him as a Brother, but alſo when occaſion ſhould offer, would ſooner take him into conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion then any other.</hi> — Really ſuch a thing was never in my heart, nor did I in my judgement think him equal with the meaneſt of all the Brethren of our Faculty in theſe parts, as to the practical part of Phyſick, though by this Artifice I gueſs his deſign is to level them all. But the ground of the ſtory is this.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106770:9"/>
            <p>This Apothecary after my Book in Anſwer to Mr. <hi>S.</hi> was come out, came to me at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and told me he had read my Book, &amp;c. and had made that Errand to me to Endeavor a Reconciliation betwixt us, deſiring carneſtly, that we might be in Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and joyn hand in hand, as there ſhould be occaſion. — I told him I had ſaid what I intended, and my Vitriol and Gall were ſpent in thoſe lines, and if he were ſo ſatisfyed, and did deſire it, I could embrace him in all <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Charitie even as a Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther (following that rule of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour Mat.</hi> 18.22. and farther that I would not refuſe to joyn with him, if we were conſulted together, as with any other. Thus I thought my ſelf on that occaſion obliged to ſay, and repeat as often as he urged the motion: But to wreſt that my readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to comply in a <hi>Chriſtian duty</hi> into a <hi>Puſillanimos daſt ardy</hi> is both <hi>unchriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> and <hi>unreaſonable.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106770:10"/>
            <p>Are not theſe dangerous men that I have to deal withall, from whom a man ſhall find nothing ſhort of the lie caſt in his face? I ſay again, there is no plainer ſigne of a deſperate Cauſe, then when men ſeek out ſuch a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But he ſayes I ſupplyed my defect of Arguments with Taunts and Scoffs at him.</hi> — As for my Arguments, he is not fit to be a <hi>Judge</hi> of them; they lye at the mercy of the <hi>judicious Reader</hi> to whom I ſubmit all, for I am as litle apt to defend my own defects, as to ſearch our thoſe of others. — I muſt confeſs I did think ſlightly of that Adverſary, from whom I had received ſuch rude language without a cauſe, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I thought fit to go merily on with him, both for my own recreation and the Readers, having a minde as tis ſaid of the Poets, <hi>aut prodeſſe aut delectare,</hi> as the motter did lead me. Not have I ſpoken to any mans diſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage out of the leaſt deſign or ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſity,
<pb facs="tcp:106770:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>and therefore though poſſibly I need the Readers pardon, yet I expect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one from him. But if my Paſſions went hand in hand with the intereſt of Truth which I deſign to maintain and ſtand by, I hope that will plead for me, and procure me a pardon from all that are ingenuous, and profeſs themſelves Lovers of Truth.</p>
            <p>There are many more ridiculous girds againſt me in that Book called <hi>Vindication, &amp;c.</hi> not worthy to be mentioned, which the wiſe Reader will diſcern to be ſufficiently ſcurri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous.</p>
            <p>But to proceed. What have we in that Book, to <hi>Vindicate</hi> his abuſe and contempt of <hi>Galen, Hippocrates, Dioſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corides,</hi> and all the Learned Princes in Phiſick, and our Modern Writers too, with their method, which I have defended, (<hi>p.</hi> 205.) againſt his manifold Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies? But what aggravates his crime, he perſiſts in the ſame, and after reproof, yet hardens his heart; unleſs
<pb facs="tcp:106770:11"/>we ſhall believe that <hi>Catilines</hi> latter Conſpiracy were ſufficient to <hi>vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate</hi> his former; or that Crimes are <hi>juſtified</hi> by Majoration.</p>
            <p>How does he <hi>Vindicate</hi> himſelf from that ſhameful guilt of deriding thoſe of our Faculty that travaile beyond Sea to ſtudy in <hi>Forreign Vniverſities,</hi> and his <hi>Scurrilous</hi> gibing at thoſe <hi>Learned Profeſſors</hi> about their Readings to the young Students, whom he ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verely taxes with ignorance at their return. (<hi>p.</hi> 206.) What dos he ſay for himſelf, in that he trampled upon the <hi>Univerſities,</hi> and all the Arts, calling it a <hi>trifling of time at the Univerſities,</hi> (<hi>p</hi> 107. <hi>in the frothy Studies of Logick, Ethicks, Phyſicks, and Metaphiſicks?</hi> for all which things I have chaſtiſed him in my Anſwer; but it apears, not enough.</p>
            <p>Had theſe things been known in that <hi>neighbour Univerſity</hi> beyond Sea, where, after a Fourthnights ſo jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and a private Examination like
<pb facs="tcp:106770:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>that of Schoolboyes when they are admitted Freſhmen into our Colledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, he was dubd with a degree <hi>Sub Camino,</hi> to wit, under the Chimney, as I heard himſelf confeſs to a Learned Scotch-man, <hi>Mr. Richard Douglas,</hi> who was well acquainted with the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes of that <hi>Univerſitie:</hi> So called <hi>Sub Camino,</hi> on purp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe to diſtinguiſh it from that degree of Honour which is taken publikely in the <hi>Schools,</hi> and which the Scholes of that nation ſcorn to take, but is conferred only on Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen or Noble mens Servants who have a mind to ſee the Ceremonies; and ſignifies no more, then if one of our Profeſſours ſhould jocularly make a Doctor in his Chamber, to gratifie ſome Friends in ſhewing them the Ceremonies of that degree, and ought not to ſet as a Title in a Book. I ſay had theſe things been known, we had not heard of this Leaden Title, the publication whereof gave occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the ſetting out of this imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb facs="tcp:106770:12"/>Piece; nor is it to be accounted any increaſe of his Reputation to have added this to his <hi>Batchelors of Arts</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree. I mention this on purpoſe to give a caution to the <hi>Heads</hi> of our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities,</hi> that when they admit Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men <hi>ad eundem gradum,</hi> they may di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh betwixt that degree taken in the <hi>Schools,</hi> and that <hi>ſub Camino,</hi> ſince they have not any degree of that metal.</p>
            <p>I hope no man that has a value for Learning will miſinterpret this digreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, which is deſigned meerly to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Honour of <hi>School-Degrees,</hi> which is one main ſpur to the ſtudy of the Arts.</p>
            <p>But I may not pretermit his vain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glorious challenge he ſends me, <hi>to take an equal number of Patients with me of them that come to the Spaw, and which of us ſhould make the beſt and ſpeedieſt Cure ſhould wear the Bayes.</hi> — Ay, this is that he would fain be at, to try Experiments on mens Bodies, which he propoſed before in his <hi>Hydrol. Chym.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:106770:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>and for which I did a little ſchool him, <hi>p.</hi> 262. of my Anſwer. But aſſuredly his tools he works withal are ſo well known, even by his own deſcription of them in that Book, that no wiſe man is willing to try their temper. But where is <hi>Modeſty</hi> all this while? ſurely that Vertue has left the Earth, or Young Men whom it would well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come, having put on <hi>Impudence</hi> inſtead thereof, being paſt both <hi>Counſel</hi> and <hi>Correction,</hi> hereby verifying that old Adage, <hi>Qui ſemel Modeſtiae limites tranſiliit, niſi cito caſtigetur, gnaviter evadet impudens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning Cures I have done at the Spaw, I have writ at large in my firſt Book, and modeſtly too, and have further occaſion to mention more in this, and could be much more copi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous if it were needful, having been ſufficiently tried in that particular; and if he be not ſatisfied, he may fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enquire, and then make report. <hi>Ahab</hi> King of Iſrael has left a good
<pb facs="tcp:106770:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>Rule, <hi>Let not him that puts on his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour boaſt like him that puts it off.</hi> 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 20.11.</p>
            <p>I remember I once cured a <hi>mad</hi> man at <hi>Scarb.</hi> with the help of the Water, and ſome other things that I added, who being very poor, was ſent to me above fifty miles, at the Pariſhes charge where he had lived. If ſuch an one ſhould come, perhaps he might be content to be managed by him, but I ſuſpect ſcarce any man ſhort of him (except his Relations) will make ſuch a choice.</p>
            <p>But I haſten. This Book called <hi>A Vindication, &amp;c.</hi> is like a <hi>Beggars</hi> cloak made up of many patches, (as his manner of writing is) that have no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendency on one another, but are here drawn in together to make a medley.</p>
            <p>He tells a long ſtory about the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of Alome at <hi>Whitby.</hi> Concerning which Captain <hi>Francis Cummin</hi> who is the manager of thoſe works, did of his ow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> accord, and without asking
<pb facs="tcp:106770:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>tell me, there is not any thing of truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it, and Mr. <hi>John Thomlinſon</hi> who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ves alſo in <hi>Whitby,</hi> and is the Alome Merchant, aſſerts the ſame.</p>
            <p>Next he has his ſupplements to the <hi>Sweet Spaw</hi> and <hi>Sulphur well</hi> at <hi>Knareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rough:</hi> A large diſquiſition that ſeems; for juſt nothing but to keep him im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinently buſie, and ſet his wits a working. But I am loth to interrupt him in that enquiry, ſince 'tis to be doubted, if he had not that to do, he would do worſe.</p>
            <p>Then he gives an Anſwer to certain Queries ingeniouſly propounded by Dr. <hi>Foot,</hi> concerning the cauſe of the ſudden loſs of the vertues of Mineral Waters, mentioned in <hi>Numb.</hi> 52. <hi>of the Philoſ. Tranſact. p.</hi> 1050. in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to the Enlarged Account of my Book, the Learned Publiſher thereof was pleaſed to give (<hi>Num.</hi> 51.) Dr. <hi>Foot</hi>'s main Query is, <hi>Whither all thoſe ſorts of waters being cloſe ſtopped, or car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried to ſome diſtance, do not let fall a
<pb facs="tcp:106770:14"/>yellowſhip ſediment, or Ochre, and ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come effete in their vertues, or loſe their purging property.</hi> He anſwers in the <hi>affirmative, p.</hi> 122. and that in refe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence to <hi>Scarb. Spaw,</hi> which he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends to make out by Experiments. I anſwered <hi>negatively,</hi> as may appear in <hi>Numb.</hi> 60. <hi>of the Phil. Tranſ. p.</hi> 1079. and therein I appeal to all thoſe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreds of Witneſſes who have drunk <hi>Scarb.</hi> Water at diſtance, Whether they do not find a yellow ſediment in the bottom of their veſſels, and yet the water continues purgative. And to make ſure work, he repeats the ſame again (<hi>p.</hi> 126.) in Anſwer to the eighth Query. But thus the Reader may plainly diſcern what meaſure of Knowledge this Man has in <hi>Scarbrough Spaw,</hi> while he underſtands not this main point wherein <hi>Scarbrough</hi> Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter differs from others of this Nation. And then what cauſe there was for all the heat and rude language that he has given me about that ſubject.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:106770:14"/>
            <p>There again (<hi>p.</hi> 127.) he ſeverely <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cuſes me to have ſaid theſe words, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>That Scarb. Waters loſe all their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rtue, yea and their quantity and bulk alſo, though in glaſſes and under the Her mitick Seales, if removed from the Fountain.</hi> Let him find thoſe words, or that ſenſe either, and Ile be his Bond man. If any man has miſtaken me, it is not my fault. In <hi>pag.</hi> 100. of my Anſwer, to which that ſeems to refer, I admit of an <hi>alteration</hi> by car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage through the loſs of the <hi>volatile</hi> parts or ſpirits; but I do not therefore ſay, they <hi>loſe all their vertue,</hi> for they purge ſtill, only I think they open not obſtructions ſo well, nor are ſo plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to the palate. I tell indeed that <hi>Frambeſarius</hi> and <hi>Heers</hi> do affirm, that the <hi>German</hi> Waters carried at di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, though cloſely ſealed up in Bottles, loſe ſomething of their bulk and quantity; but I did not affirm that of <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> only infered that my aſſertion touching the loſs of
<pb facs="tcp:106770:15"/>the volatile Spirits was no Paradox, while thoſe other are leſſened even in their quantity. But he has accuſtomed me to bear ſuch charges, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am the better provided to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo them.</p>
            <p>Then he tells how he Anatomized the <hi>German Spaw</hi> in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> where probably he is opinionated that he has made ſome great diſcovery: and laſtly he concludes with his Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions on the Diſſection of a woman who died of the <hi>Jaundice,</hi> when he wonders at every thing that he Saw, as <hi>Ston<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s</hi> in the <hi>Gaul, Schirrus</hi> on the <hi>Heart,</hi> and ſo he might well, for I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve it was the firſt; (though I do not charge him for that, ſince he is wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to learn, notwithſtanding in his other Book I found him ſpurning at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natomy.</hi>) So he tels us of the under part of the Left Lobe of the Liver, but he forgot to ſay that it was done with a left handed Knife.</p>
            <p>But he tells us he ſaw ſomething
<pb facs="tcp:106770:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>more, and that was, another woman Diſſected there that dyed of a <hi>Syncope,</hi> I ſuppoſe ſo will he; Although he ſays its more then Probable that ſhe dy'd o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſome other diſeaſe. — It ſeems ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing there was that made the old w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> die. But the <hi>Schirrus</hi> tumour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> or the <hi>Heart</hi> ſticks on his <hi>Stomach,</hi> ai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he cannot digeſt it, for he tells of<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, of lies again, yet ſo confuſedly, as its hard to judge whether he means that Heart did belong to the latter or the formed woman. But it may be he was in hafted and ſo am I to have done with h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> At laſt he tells how the cauſe of that <hi>Jaundice</hi> was variouſly diſputed, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> he ſayes in ſuch a portion of language as will make any man laugh, be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e never ſo grave.</p>
            <p>The truth is his whole Book is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a clattering of fond words. Or if you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pleaſe like the ſhearing of a Svvi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> where there is a great Cry, but lit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:106770:16"/>Wool. What do his multitudes of Experiments ſignifie, vverein he ſo much prides himſelf? juſt nothing if they vvere true and vvould certainly fall out. I think never any man loved more to hear himſelf talk, and what he fancies muſt be preſently publiſhed, be it true or falſe, real or imaginary; and like a Child he will have every one to know that <hi>he has a Rattle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have but one word in reference to this other Author <hi>D.T.</hi> and then I have done. He has more ſeverely diſparag'd the Spaw then the other, but he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducesno teſtimony but from his own experience, which in Reaſon cannot be judged Authentick enough, eſpecially when I come to examine it. I have <hi>Right Honourable, Right Worſhipful, Reverend,</hi> and <hi>Welbeloved</hi> on my ſide to witneſs with me; if ever he ſhall let fly again to accuſe the Water of any Faults, it is but reaſonable that he ſhould name his Witneſſes and their
<pb facs="tcp:106770:16"/>Qualities or Reputation; for his own Magiſterial Affirmation will not be deemed ſufficient.</p>
            <p>And if either of theſe two Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſhall yet further abound in their own ſenſe, and rejoyn, it ſhall be a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry great povocati on that ſhall make me reply having ſaid enough upon this Subject, and perhaps as much as it can well bear, unleſs I ſhall be hurried un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Tautalogies,</hi> which I love not, though probably ſome body elſe may give Anſwer. And indeed it ſeems to me to be very reaſonable at length to put an end to Diſputing. <hi>Ne nimium alter cando veritas amittatur,</hi> as <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crobius</hi> ſayes. Beſides that I am wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the interruption of my other Practical Studies. Farewel.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>York.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 3. 1671.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:106770:17"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:106770:17"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER To all that D. <hi>TONST ALL</hi> Has Writ, or ſhall hereafter Writ, Againſt <hi>SCARBRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH SPAW.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>PLutarch</hi> reports of <hi>Themiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles,</hi> that while he was young he was often wont to ſay, that he had not yet done any thing <hi>Notable,</hi> for as much as he had not contracted Envy, nor met with any Oppoſition: I am not conceited of any thing that I have done, (ſo for a I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:106770:18"/>know my own Heart) but yet if I may take alm <hi>a Poſteriori,</hi> from the Envy and Oppoſition that I have met with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout writing upon the Subject of the <hi>Spaw</hi> at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> it will appear there is ſomewhat in't, more than at firſt I thought on. I am ſure of one thing, I have diſcovered a very <hi>Notable Wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r,</hi> and therein with all fidelity have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to ſerve my Country. If I erred in the manner of doing, 'twas much againſt my will, yet I have heard on't to the purpoſe.</p>
            <p>At the firſt, a <hi>Confederacy</hi> threw dirt in my Face, which I hope I have waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed off in a good meaſure; Now comes Doctor <hi>Tonſtall,</hi> and he throws dirt in the <hi>Spaw,</hi> but it being a Quick-ſpring, 'twill in time work it our, though I ſhould be ſilent, as indeed at the firſt coming out of his P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ece (intituled, <hi>Scarbrough Spaw Spagyrically anatomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed</hi>) I had thought to have done, and ſo to have contented my ſelf with the ingenious Anſwer, of one to a like piece <hi>Vidi &amp; Riſi,</hi> ſince the weakneſs of his Arguments, and meanneſs of his deſign as: obvious to every Reader.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:106770:18"/>Yet being done by a Brother of the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>culty, and ſuch an One as of whom I had before given an Honourable Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>imony, (though he has now changed his mind) and obſerving that ſome few if facile Tempers, or weaker Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments were a little ſtartled at ſomwhat that he has objected againſt the <hi>Spaw,</hi> I judged it neceſſary to convince my Brother of his Errour, and to cleanſe the <hi>Spaw</hi> of the dirt he has left in it, wherein though my work is like that of <hi>Hercules,</hi> when he cleanſed the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gean</hi> Stable, yet my Labour is nothing like his, for I ſhall wind up all in a few ſheets.</p>
            <p>He ſays in his Preface, <hi>he wou'd have what he has written to ſerve as an Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix to my Latine Copy, which I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed on the</hi> Spaw, <hi>and he would cloth it in like Faſhion.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Tonſtalt</hi> ſingles out the Author by name.</note> — Thus he has called me out to a publick encounter with him, without any previous Provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on given on my ſide.— I hope he will ſo do as here he ſays, when he ſhall be deſired, and there is need; in the mean time I ſhall ſay with <hi>Africa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us, Non amo nimium diligentes.</hi>— He
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:106770:19"/>has ſeen ſomewhat of what I have done in that point, and here we have ſuch an Eſſay of his Art, that he muſt give me ſome time to demur, before I call for his help.</p>
            <p>He profeſſes himſelf to be my <hi>Friend,</hi> and therefore I'le treat him accordingly, and in point of Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip will mildly endeavour to clear up his Eye-ſight, that he may diſcern what is Truth, and ſo ſet him right in his way.</p>
            <p>He ſays <hi>he walks uniformly betwixt my Library and Maſter</hi> Sympſon <hi>Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory, otherwiſe he ſhould ſuſpect him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for a lame Phyſician.</hi>— I am glad my Friend is ſo well fitted for his Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment; he is an <hi>Ambidexter, &amp; in utrumque paratus:</hi> a <hi>Janus</hi> that looks both ways, <hi>Quem nulla ciconia pinſit.</hi> He has a two-edged Sword, with which he cuts down Diſeaſes, a <hi>Library,</hi> and a <hi>Labora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ory. Hippocrates</hi> and <hi>Helmont</hi> (he ſays) <hi>are the two great Lights that rule in his Hemiſphere.</hi>— No mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel then if he ſees more than the moſt of his B e bren, (<hi>vide</hi> p. 14. and 42.) where he applauds himſelf and taxes
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:106770:19"/>them, and more into <hi>Scarbrough Spaw</hi> in two Summers, than I in thirty: Let no man henceforth ſuſpect him for a ſame Phyſician.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galen</hi> is ſlieghted by Doctor <hi>Tonſtall.</hi>
               </note> Only <hi>Galen</hi> he is not taken withal, whoſe Method he'l allow to be no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Rational, then as he writes after the old man his Maſters Copy; he dares not further ſpeak for him.— Poor <hi>Galen!</hi> I have had to do with Mr. <hi>S.</hi> and now with Doctor <hi>T.</hi> an angry Adverſary, and a — Friend, and I find that neither of them are reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to him. How ſeverely is he cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by ſome men now a days! I am ſure it was not always ſo! Methinks none ſhould take upon them to judge ſo great a <hi>Prince in Phyſick,</hi> but ſuch a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> know they can do better. If my <hi>Friend</hi> dares not ſpeak for him, but he muſt want ſo <hi>good an Advocate.</hi> Well! Let both their works ſtand forth in open Court to plead for their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Authors, and then let the learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed give judgement according to their merits.</p>
            <p>Here I crave the Readers patience a while, till I make a ſhort digreſſion,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106770:20"/>and tell the world what <hi>Galens</hi> parts and works have been, and what he has done in the Art of Phyſick, by which it will appear what real ground there is for his Name <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o be ſo trampled on, and his Authority and Labour ſo ſlieghtly eſteemed, as he is by many in this our Age.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The firſt riſe of Phyſick.</note> After the Art of Phyſick was found out, which is attributed by ancient Writers to <hi>Apollo,</hi> as the firſt Inventer, and imported to his Son <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> who poliſhed it much from its rude Notions; He trained up his two Sons <hi>Podalirius</hi> and <hi>Machaon</hi> in the ſame Art: The former addicted himſelf to the ſtudy of inward Remedies, and the latter to outward Applications; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning whom <hi>Homer</hi> gives his Teſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, as alſo <hi>Suidas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe kept it as <hi>a Secret</hi> in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> for many Generations, till at leng h <hi>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ppocrates,</hi> who was the eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eenth from <hi>Aeſculapius,</hi> po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſhed it ſtill further, and having it ſeems a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous pub ick Spirit, drew it into a form o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> method, and expoſed it to the world; Having not only the helps of
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106770:20"/>his Anceſtors, and their Experimen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut the opportunity of tranſcribing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Records which he found in the Temple at <hi>Coos</hi> dedicated to <hi>Aeſcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ius,</hi> where the Prieſts <hi>ex Officio</hi> were bound to take an Account of all Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that had been recovered out of any S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ckneſs, and to tranſcribe bo h the Symptomes of their Diſeaſes, and the Remedies by which they were cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. And this was the Cuſtome in <hi>Aegypt</hi> alſo; yea, and in <hi>Arabia</hi> and <hi>Perſia</hi> to this day, as I have ſeveral times heard Sir <hi>Thomas Herbert</hi> tell, where (he ſays) the ſick people are brought into the Market-place, that any paſſenger may enquire of their caſe, to whom they uſually give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, and in caſe any man do know a Remedy for ſuch a Malady, he is bound by his Religion to miniſter help, and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng found healing it is recorded by the Prieſts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hippocrates</hi> being learned to a <hi>Prodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y,</hi> and thus furniſht with extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary help, and living to a great Age, (to wit) a hundred and nine years (as <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ranus</hi> reports) adorned this Art with
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:106770:21"/>many grave Sentences, and authentick Aphoriſms relating to the ſeveral parts of Phyſick, and from his own large Experience has left many <hi>excellent Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines,</hi> and a <hi>Method</hi> which we find of ſingular uſe to this day, now after 2000. years, and ſo probably muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to the end of the World.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Several Sects in Phyſick.</note> H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s Writings gave an opportunity to others to ſtep in to the Study of the Art, among whom were <hi>Diosles Cariſtius</hi> and <hi>Petron,</hi> then <hi>Praxagoras</hi> and <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> then <hi>Herophilus</hi> and <hi>Eraſiſtratus,</hi> all theſe proceeded in divers methods, and ſo fell into Factions. Alſo <hi>Mene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates,</hi> whoſe pride was ſuch that he called himſelf <hi>Jupiter,</hi> and wore a golden Crown. He would never un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke a Patient, unleſs he would ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige himſelf under his hand-writing to be his Servant and A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tendant when ever he ſhould call; ſo as he was went to lead about whole Troops of Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents, as ſo many Trophees of his Cures, all whom he called by the names of <hi>the Gods,</hi> as <hi>Athenaeus</hi> and <hi>Hegeſander</hi> make mention.</p>
            <p>After theſe ſtarted up <hi>Serapion, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollonius,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106770:21"/>Glaucias</hi> and <hi>Heraclius Taren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinus,</hi> with ſeveral others who called themſelves <hi>Empiricks,</hi> and ſo made a new Sect.</p>
            <p>Then followed <hi>Aſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>epiades</hi> and <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſon,</hi> who inſtituted another Sect cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Methodiſts.</hi> After thoſe <hi>Cornelius Celſus</hi> ſtepped into the Profeſſion at <hi>Rome,</hi> being the moſt Learned of all the Latine Payſicians: He lived in the time of our Saviour, and was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly ſtilled <hi>Latine-Hippocrates,</hi> and well does he deſerve to be accounted one of the Princes in Phyſick, as he is ranked by the Learned. After him was <hi>Archigenes</hi> of whom <hi>Juvenal</hi> does ſeveral times make Honourable menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, who lived in the Reign of <hi>Adrion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The decay of Phyſick.</note> To be ſhort, then came up <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies</hi> the moſt proud and malepert Fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that ever was in the world, who as <hi>Pliny</hi> ſaith (<hi>lil.</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Nat. H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. cap.</hi> 1.) madly raved againſt all the moſt excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Phyſicians that had been before him, contemn ig them all, even <hi>Hip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrates</hi> himſelf, accuſing them of groſs ignorance, while he boaſted egregi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly of himſelf and his method, as in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106770:22"/>his Letter to <hi>Nero</hi> may appear cited by <hi>Galen</hi> (<hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Meth. cap.</hi> 11.) al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though yet he knew nothing of ſolid Learning, or the Art of Phyſick, but depraved it with an unwholeſome Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, and a number of unſound me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines.— Were I a <hi>Pythagorean,</hi> and did believe a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, I ſhould think his Soul had been ſeveral times ſince tranſlated into another Body.</p>
            <p>Thus was this <hi>Noble Art</hi> lacerated and torn by various Factions, the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe humours of ſome diſquieting the peace of others, the wholeſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Principles raſed, and the Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe differing in every Country, while yet <hi>every Quack</hi> magnified his own way, and mens lives were moſt in jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy in the hands of them who pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended moſt to preſerve them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Its repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion by <hi>Galen.</hi>
               </note> In the midſt of this decay ſteps up <hi>Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en, (vid.)</hi> in the ſecond Century from the Nativity of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> and 600. years after <hi>Hippocrates.</hi> He was certainly the moſt Learned of his Age in all the parts of uſeful Learning, as his voluminous Writings do ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly make out, but eſpecially in Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106770:22"/>even to a <hi>Prodigy;</hi> which Art be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing left imperfect by <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> and not fully elaborated as Himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes in his Let<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er to <hi>Democritus,</hi> where (he ſays) that though he had now lived to be old, yet neither He, nor yet <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſculapius,</hi> nor any that he had met with, had attained to any conſiderable height in the Profeſſion, but muſt leave it imperfect: But <hi>Galen</hi> undertook this task, and has brought it to ſuch a perfection, as no Art beſides in the World can pretend to, and thus not only in the judgement of the <hi>Antient Princes</hi> in Phyſick, who followed him,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galen</hi> in high e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Antients.</note> as <hi>Paulus, Aetius, Oribaſius,</hi> &amp;c. who have tranſcribed moſt choice Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and long diſcourſes out of him word for word, as not being able, or not needing to adde to him, but alſo in the Suffrage of our beſt <hi>Modern Writers.</hi> What was obſcure in <hi>Hippo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crates</hi> he has cleared up, he has diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſht of things that differed, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied what was defective. Not that I would make him to be infallible or that nothing has been added ſince, or yet may not be, but that certainly he was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:106770:23"/>the greateſt <hi>Benefactor</hi> to, and <hi>Poliſher</hi> of <hi>Medicine,</hi> that ever was in the world. He had indeed <hi>Hirpocrates</hi> his Foundation to build upon, but aſſured<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly thereupon he raiſed a moſt adm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſtructure,</p>
            <p>He encountred the ſeveral Sects I mentioned, diſcovered plainly their impoſtures, their ragged Methods and unwholeſome Medicines, and enrich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Art with <hi>excellent Tractats</hi> upon every part of Phyſick, and innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>rare Remedies,</hi> which retain his Name to this day: And hereto he was enabled not only by the help of the <hi>ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> man his Maſter,</hi> (as our Author calls him) but alſo by his own <hi>prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous</hi> parts, length of time that was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them, and his own large Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence through age, for he lived till he was an <hi>hundred and forty years</hi> old, and therefore probably he might be truſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, though he ſhould in ſome things d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ffer from his Maſters Copy.</p>
            <p>While he lived he was eſteemed the prime Star of the firſt magnitude in his O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>be, and of ſingular account with the Emperour <hi>Antoninus,</hi> and the many
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106770:23"/>Volumes he has left behind him, have begot him a Reputation, which Envy can never blaſt among ſuch as are Learned. This made <hi>Fuchſius</hi> cry <hi>Non dubium eſt quin à Deo excitatus,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">As alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Neotericks</note> &amp;c. to wit, no doubt but he was raiſed up by God to repair the Art of Phyſick, which was extreamly ſhattered in theſe times (<hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>inſtit. med.</hi>) And <hi>Valleriola</hi> ſays of him, <hi>Quem Heroa potiù ac daemonem, quàm Hominem ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellare ſuo ſanè merito poſſumus;</hi> he knows not whether he ſhould not call him ſome Cae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſtial Hero, or Angel, rather than a Man, ſuch was his merit in his eſteem (<hi>Loc. com. lib.</hi> 1.) To theſe I'le add but one more, which I find in <hi>Euſebius</hi> his Eccleſiaſtical Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry (<hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap. ult.</hi>) who tells that he was <hi>worſhipped</hi> (ſuch was their Opinion of him) by ſome of the Heathens <hi>as a God.</hi> He was indeed no Chriſtian; though I read, that hearing of the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racles that were done in thoſe Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive times, by the followers of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles of our <hi>Saviour,</hi> in the curing of diſeaſes by a word. He fell into <hi>Admiration,</hi> and made a Voyage to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106770:24"/>
               <hi>Judaea</hi> to know the certainty of it by his own view, but as God would have it died by the way.</p>
            <p>Thus far I thought fit to digreſs on this occaſion, that I might give ſome account to the world of this great <hi>Prince in Phyſick, Galen,</hi> and to make it out that he was no Trifle, as ſome would render him, but that his Name was, and is yet in Reputation among ſuch <hi>as underſtand him well.</hi> I now pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
            <p>Dr. <hi>Tonſtall</hi> ſays, <hi>he hopes it will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that in this Tract he has been very candid towards me, and ſaid nothing</hi> ad Perſonam, <hi>but</hi> ad Rem.— 'Twere well if I could find it ſo; I think no man that has read his Book is of that mind; but ſeeing he pretends it, I ſhall willingly leap over a great many of thoſe Reflexions <hi>ad Perſonam,</hi> (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides what has been told me by Perſons of known integrity of his liberty of Speech) and only examine ſuch as are <hi>ad Rem,</hi> if any be ſo, wherein I'le uſe as much Candour as the Nature of my task can admit.</p>
            <p>He ſays, <hi>he has not concerned himſelf
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106770:24"/>in a word which I have ſaid in my two Books, but only what was neceſſary</hi> ſe De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendendo. — Really I wonder at this Expreſſion! Who ever offended him, that he ſhould ſtand up in his own <hi>defence?</hi> Is not he the Aſſailant and Aggreſſor? What was there in my Books that concerned him? Indeed I mentioned his Name <hi>p.</hi> 107. of my Anſwer to <hi>Hydrol. Chimica</hi> with ſome ſincere reſpect, wherein he has made it appear that I was miſtaken, and therefore I'le henceforth <hi>reſume</hi> ſince he has <hi>recanted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>He boaſts of his Mechanical Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, whereby he makes cut the Mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Principles of the</hi> Spaw, <hi>and preſents them to our Senſes;</hi> and ſays, <hi>that my failure was, that I left off where I ſhould have begun.</hi>— To this I ſay, I have ever obſerved the greateſt Cenſors ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther produce nothing of their own, or what is more ridiculous than any thing they reprehend. Much of ill Nature, and a very little Judgement, go a great way in finding the miſtakes of Writers, eſpecially when a deſign is at the bottome.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106770:25"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dr <hi>T</hi> diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenuous towards the Author</note> He ſays, <hi>after I had obſerved what was moſt conſpicuous about the</hi> Spaw, <hi>and found that the Gall tinctured the Water of a dark purple colour, I contented my ſelf with fair probabilities for aſſerting the five Principles.</hi>— So again (<hi>p.</hi> 19.) he cites a paſſage out of my Book, where I ſay the Principles cannot be ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted further then I had expreſſed,— he adds of his own— <hi>Namely by putting gall to the Water,</hi> &amp;c. and then he Comments upon this Aſſertion in both places with reference both to my ſelf and others, to whom he undertakes (though impertinently enough) to read a <hi>Lectu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e of Anatomy and Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental Phyloſophy,</hi> and tells of things that no man ever doubted of, or in the leaſt oppoſed that underſtands any thing in Phyſick, but teaches us that <hi>the ſeparation of the Principles ſhould have been made by fire.</hi>— Thus he would gladly make the world be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, eſpecially thoſe that have not met with my Books, that all that I have ſaid to make out the five Principles was but this, that the Water is tinctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red black by the addition of Gall.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106770:25"/>But I would ask him if this be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ndneſs of a Friend (as he profeſſes himſelf to be) to ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e thus, and to leave out the reſt of my Arguments of demonſtration, whereby I made them out.</p>
            <p>This indeed I mention (<hi>p.</hi> 9. of my firſt Book) as a T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ken of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> to which there I added the <hi>acid taſte</hi> and <hi>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ky ſmell</hi> (<hi>2ly.</hi>) to prove <hi>A ume,</hi> I mention its cur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of Milk, and the bubbling noice it makes when its boiled near the bottom, which I made out to be a peculiar property of <hi>Alume,</hi> from the teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mony of good Natura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts. (<hi>3ly.</hi>) To prove <hi>Iron,</hi> I mention the black ſediment that falls to the bottome of the veſſel after Gall is put into it, which calc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nes red being near of kin to Vitriol, which therefore (<hi>p.</hi> 10.) I called <hi>Ferrum Vitriolatum</hi> or <hi>Vitriolum ferrugineum;</hi> beſides the uſe I made of it inwardly, wherein I find it to perform the ſame intentions with <hi>Iron</hi> or <hi>Steel,</hi> and that it tinges the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crements black, as all our preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of <hi>Iron</hi> do; together with the yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Sediment which falls to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106770:26"/>of the veſſel, when it is carried at diſtance, being much like unto <hi>Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Martis,</hi> as I expreſſed it (<hi>p.</hi> 11.) and he himſelf calls it ſo (<hi>p.</hi> 57) when he obſerved it in the ſpout of <hi>Knares<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>br. Spaw.</hi> (<hi>4ly.</hi>) To prove <hi>Nitre,</hi> I tell of its ſhooting into <hi>Stiriae</hi> or Ice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſickles, which is the peculiar property of <hi>Nitre.</hi> (<hi>5ly.</hi>) I ſay what <hi>Salt</hi> it has, it takes from the Sea, although I declared it to have but very little Salt in it.</p>
            <p>Then again I demonſtrate theſe from their <hi>Adjuncts,</hi> that there is a great probability that theſe are the Minerals that are in it. 1. From the veins of <hi>Nitre,</hi> which appear in the cliffe like hoar-froſt or ſnow, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minently within a few yards of the Well. (<hi>2ly.</hi>) From the many ſtones of <hi>Iron</hi> that are in the Cliffe, beſides the Earth that turns to an <hi>Iron-ſtone,</hi> and melts in the Smiths Forge like Metal. (<hi>3ly.</hi>) The abundance of <hi>Alume-ſtone</hi> that is in all that Cliffe. (<hi>4ly.</hi>) The plentiful imbibition of ſo many Minerals, which is promoted by the Acidity of the <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>;</hi> as alſo the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106770:26"/>
               <hi>Vitrioline juyce</hi> which is yellow of co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, that ſweats out of the Cliffe about 110 paces from the Spring, which he himſelf two years ago, <hi>when he had no deſign to carry on,</hi> acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to be no other then <hi>Vitriol,</hi> which gave me occaſion to mention him and his conſent therein, <hi>p.</hi> 107. of my lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Book. (<hi>5ly.</hi>) The propinquity of the Sea gives ground to many wiſe men to think it may have <hi>Salt.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides much more that I have ſaid in my latter Book to prove them all againſt that my fierce Adverſary while he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied them. and as laſt was forced to confeſs them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Royal So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciety.</note> Now while I have <hi>in terminis</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed all theſe Experimental Proofs of the five Principles, and expoſed them all not only to wiſe mens Reaſon, but alſo to the view of <hi>many Perſons of Quality,</hi> and particularly to thoſe <hi>Honourable Lords and Gentlemen of the Royal Society</hi> the laſt year, to whom I preſented by that eminently Learned and obliging Gentleman <hi>Henry Olden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg,</hi> Eſq. ſeven or eight ſorts of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts and Spirits, which I took out of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106770:27"/>this Spaw-water, which thoſe <hi>Noble Worthies</hi> were pleaſed to receive with <hi>ſom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>isf<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ction;</hi> a full <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſcription of which Extracts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> the Reader may find in number 60 of the <hi>Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophical Tranſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ctions,</hi> with my Letter at large: I ſay, while I have thus fully and plainly made them out, it was not <hi>candid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y</hi> done of him to mention that of <hi>ting<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng with Gall,</hi> and to leave out the reſt, on purpoſe to render me ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous. But thus he deals with me as <hi>Hanun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> did with K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng <hi>Davids</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, 2 <hi>Sam</hi> 10.4. of whom the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>xt ſaith, <hi>that he ſhaved off the half of their beards, and cut off their garments in the middle even to their Buttocks, and ſent them away on purpoſe to make them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed.</hi> — But this did ſo exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly diſoblige K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>vid,</hi> that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came an occaſion of breaking that bond of F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſhip that had been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them.</p>
            <p>I was indeed ſhort in my firſt Book, while I di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>courſed of the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> five M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inciples, becauſe I deſigned b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>evity, yet t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> much was ſaid to make them ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. And being called
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:106770:27" rendition="simple:additions"/>into queſtion by M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>S.</hi> for this very thin, I refer to the Learned, whether in my Reply to him, I have not ſtood m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd. But this alſo our Author had a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to overlook, boaſting of his own <hi>Mechanical</hi> demonſtration, as if I had offered no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hing of Experiment to prove them.</p>
            <p>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d whereas he ſays (<hi>p.</hi> 20.) <hi>that fire was the proper Inſtrum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nt to eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct the ſeparation of the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nerals</hi> — a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng thereby to make the world believe I had only taken notice of the tinging with Gall, and never tried it by fire: and hence he ſays (<hi>p.</hi> 34.) <hi>that if Light had been brought in by the hand of a Chym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt</hi>— ſtrange things had been diſcovered.— I am certain of this, that the hands of ſome that call themſelves Chimiſts have brought more <hi>Heat</hi> than <hi>Light</hi> into our Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. But thus it ſeems, let but ſome men aſſume this title of a Chimiſt, and they take upon them boldly to ſay what they liſt, as if thereby they had got a Patent for freedome of Language.</p>
            <p>Did not I mention a Body of Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals (to wit) an ounce in five quarts of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106770:28"/>the water, which may be extracted ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by Diſtillation, or Evaporation over the fire? (<hi>p.</hi> 10. And notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding it contradicts what he would here impoſe upon me, that I only try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Water by Gall; Does not he himſelf cite a paſſage of mine (<hi>p.</hi> 151.) where I had been diſcourſing concerning this Body of Minerals, which in that place I ſaid cannot be extracted without a <hi>long and vehement fire?</hi> — What makes all this dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble dealing for advantage? Such Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifice is very unbecoming, and (to uſe his own word) ſavours more of a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanical</hi> than <hi>Academical</hi> demonſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. If this be <hi>Friendly,</hi> or <hi>Manly,</hi> (to ſay no more) I neither underſtand what is <hi>Friendly,</hi> nor <hi>Humane.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>he carps, becauſe I ſaid they cannot be further ſeparated than I had expreſſed.</hi>— I am certain theſe Minerals are ſo united in their Subject, the Water, as that when they come under the moſt <hi>Critical</hi> Scrutiny, <hi>never a one of them</hi> will be found to be intire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſuch, but a quite other thing, or <hi>ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium neutrum.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:106770:28" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes his levity.</note> (<hi>Pag.</hi> 13.) He confeſſes ſome Levity of Opinion he had of late been guilty of, in reference to theſe two Northern Spaws at <hi>Scarb.</hi> and <hi>Knaresb.</hi> one year perſwading his Friends to go to <hi>Scarb.</hi> and the very next year to <hi>Knaresb.</hi> This he excuſes from his own Practiſe, <hi>that he commended no other to them than be took himſelf, and then he wiſhes that all Phyſicians were bound with this girdle,</hi> propounding therein himſelf as a Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terr. — If he means that all were bound to be like him in <hi>Levity</hi> and <hi>Wavering,</hi> I know no man that will ſay <hi>Amen.</hi> Phyſicians ought better to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Remedies they uſe: But if in his <hi>Honeſty,</hi> we will all own our Engagement to him for ſo <hi>good an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this I'le adde, he brought his Wife with him to <hi>Scarb.</hi> who there found a Cure of a Malady, which ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther his own Art and Skill, nor <hi>Kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resb. Spaw</hi> could have effected, but of this more anon.<note place="margin">He extols <hi>Scarb. Spaw.</hi>
               </note> — This convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him of the Excellency of <hi>Scarb. Spaw,</hi> on which account he magnified it exceedingly, as a rare working Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106770:29"/>while he undervalued the other of <hi>Knaresb.</hi> as much, which he accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le impregnated with any Mineral; ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and conſequently to be a du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l, heavy Water, not paſſing well through the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dy: And of this there are not a few Witneſſe, both at <hi>New<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſtle</hi> where he lives, and elſe where.</p>
            <p>On this accoun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Ann<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 1669.) he perſwaded a great many Perſons of Quality to come along with him to <hi>Scarb.</hi> wholly reſolving, as appeared to them, to deſert <hi>Knaresb.</hi> which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or above 10. years together he had fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented. But ſomewhat there was wherein (it ſeems) his Exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as fruſtrate,<note place="margin">He diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rages it, and returns to <hi>Knaresb.</hi>
               </note> ſo as he muſt reſolve to return again to <hi>Knaresb.</hi> and having a great mind to draw back his T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ain of Friends with him, and to make ſome amends for his deſerting and diſparag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Knaresb.</hi> he takes the moſt plauſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble way (ſo long as 'twill hold) to leave his dirt in <hi>Scarb. Spaw,</hi> accuſing it of ſome notorious Faults, following therein the <hi>Machiavellian</hi> Rule, <hi>Forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter incuſa aliquid haerebit;</hi> laying on load enough, in hope that ſomething
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:106770:29"/>will ſtick. Three faults eſpecialy.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Three faults in <hi>Scarb.</hi>
               </note> Firſt, <hi>That it has a petrifying proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and generates the Stone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That there are filings of Stone and G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ay in it, whereby it breeds Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions, and cauſes the Jaundice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>That it corrodes the Bowels, and cauſes a Dyſentery.</hi>— I'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e now e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> mine how he makes them out.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">It's petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying.</note> To begin with the firſt, (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t) that it is petr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fying, which I ſhall examine both in point of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> in reference to ſome P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nciple in the Water, which he confeſſes, and ſo does agree with me, and alſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Experience;</hi> and I doubt not to ſat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fie wiſe men in both, and perhaps himſelf too, that he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours under a grand miſtake in this his Aſſertion.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">arg. </seg>1</label> He finds <hi>Nitre</hi> in the <hi>Saw,</hi> and ſome ſmall matter, which after it has paſſed through the heat of the fire in Evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, will not paſs the Filter; and he finds <hi>Kircher</hi> diſcourſing <hi>de ſucco lap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>difico</hi> to affirme it to be <hi>a Nitrous Stone diſſolved in Water;</hi> this gives ground enough to him, who was catch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at advantage, to accuſe the Water to be petrifying.</p>
            <pb n="26" facs="tcp:106770:30"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A Quotati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on out of <hi>Kircher</hi> examined.</note> I ſhall as to the matter that will not paſs the Filter examine that by and by, and for <hi>Kircher,</hi> I honour him as a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arned Writer, and the Author as my <hi>Friend,</hi> but <hi>magis amica veritas.</hi> In that place <hi>Kircher</hi> is telling of ſeveral Springs, that turn Sticks, Straw, or Leaves into Stone, or at the leaſt do cover them, being laid in them ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e while with a ſtony Cruſt: Now if the <hi>Spaw</hi> have that property, of cruſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling any thing into a Stone that is laid in it, then his Quotation will require a conſideration of us, but this he af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firms not, and therefore it is imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of <hi>Nitre</hi> and <hi>Salt.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Nitre</hi> is eſteemed by all Naturaliſts to be of volatile parts, exceedingly pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netrative, and a great diſſolvent, and therefore it is (ſays Dr. <hi>Jorden</hi>) that it ſerves for the diſſolution of Metals (<hi>cap.</hi> 7.) and all that ever writ of it do agree in this verdict, yea, <hi>Kircher</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>f (<hi>lib.</hi> 6. <hi>cap. de Nitro</hi>) ſays not much leſs of it, and fixes the petrifying pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty plainly upon <hi>Salt,</hi> which he calls the proper and proximal Element of Earth, which ſubminiſters craſſneſs to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106770:30"/>all ſorts of mixt bodies. His words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re— <hi>Omnibus mixtorum ſpeciebus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>aſſitiem &amp; propriam conſiſtentiam ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iniſtrat, verumque &amp; proprium proxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>mque terroe Elementum dici debet, cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Sal ſenſibile non niſi ſubjectum ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ni <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le eſt,</hi> and a little after, ſpeaking of the difference betwixt <hi>Salt</hi> and <hi>Nitre,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e owns <hi>Nitre</hi> to partake eminently of the Elements of <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Air,</hi> and to be full of fiery ſpirits; whereas <hi>Salt</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e owns to be partaker of the two groſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Elemants <hi>Water</hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi> Now how that which is of ſuch thin, vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile, and fiery parts, ſo penetrative and diſſolvent, as that it d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſolves Metals, ſhould be the matter of a Stone, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand and not, nor (I dare ſay) does Dr. <hi>Ponſtall.</hi> It has been commended in all Ages by Phyſicians againſt the Stone, as that which they expect would diſſolve it: Yea, I appeal to Dr. <hi>T.</hi> his own verdict (<hi>p.</hi> 14.) where he ſays he preferred the <hi>Nitrous</hi> ſpring at <hi>Scarb.</hi> before the <hi>Vitrioline</hi> at <hi>Knaresb.</hi> and makes a high appeal whether it be not a more <hi>noble</hi> Principle for diſſolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or expelling the Stone. <hi>Kirch<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:106770:31"/>himſelf grants as much to any Nitrous Spring, (in the place ci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, <hi>in Conſecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>) <hi>Nitrum aquis naturalibus i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſitum purgat, incidit; penetrat, detergit, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructiones expedit, movit, prope ſi q<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> arenoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m renum veſicaeque ſulſtantiam.</hi> Eminently true concerning this Spr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng at <hi>Scarb.</hi> an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I pray how can it have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> petrifying property from <hi>Nitre</hi> which is ſo penetrative, as here we find <hi>Kir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> confeſſing.</p>
            <p>Beſides, who ever ſaw a <hi>Nitrous ſtone?</hi> Nitrou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rth is ordinary; <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rapio,</hi> and <hi>Dioſcorides</hi> tell indeed of mines of Nitre in <hi>Armenia</hi> and <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> whereas <hi>Bellonius, Pliny</hi> and <hi>Geſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> ſay its only found above the Earth, but never any mention is made of <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous ſtones,</hi> and indeed its altogether inconſiſtent with the Nature of it, which is impregnated with ſuch aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of fiery and aeriel ſpirits, as we have heard from <hi>Kircher,</hi> his Author whom he grounds upon.</p>
            <p>But this is not all, for in this point <hi>Kircher</hi> himſelf i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> extreamly rov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, and unreſolved, wherein this petrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing property ſhall reſide, and what
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106770:31"/>mineral to fix it o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, for (<hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>cap. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>gine ſucci lapid<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fici</hi>) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e lays, <hi>that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Salt, or Nitre, or A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome, or Vitriol, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>thur will ſerve to make a Water to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſte a ſtick or le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f,</hi> &amp;c. but how un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>onable a thing it is to ſuppoſe that many of theſe Minerals, that are of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th thin, hot and piercing properties, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> become the matter of a Stone, I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ave it to wiſe men to conſider of, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eupon infer that our Authors firſt Argument, drawn from the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of ſuch an uncertain and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Writer, is of no validity at all.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">arg. </seg>2</label> Secondly, <hi>He would prove the</hi> Spaw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>be petrifying by m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>king a Parallel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween it, and the dropp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng Well at</hi> K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>b <hi>which in a very ſhort time will c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver Moſs, or Straw or S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cks that are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered to lye in it, with a ſtony Cruſt.</hi> To both theſe A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ments <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e anſwer in one word: Le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> any man ſhew me a ſtone ſo generated by <hi>Scar-Water,</hi> though the trial be made from a month to ſeven years, and I'e give up the cr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">arg. </seg>3</label> Thirdly, <hi>He proves it from the muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ch-ſhells, and ſuch like things that are
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106770:32"/>found near the</hi> Spaw <hi>on the Sands, as if they were converted into Stone by the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying ſpirit that is in the Spring.</hi>— Some ſuch Shells are indeed found (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though very rarely) on thoſe Sands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſuperficies of the Earth, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeldome or never in the Cliffe (I m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> confidently ſay) or at leaſt not more than in other ſoils. Theſe lying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> upon the Sands are undoubtly caſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by the Sea, and we know ſuch thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are found in all Countries upon the Sea-coaſts, even where no ſuch Spring<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> are. Let no man laugh at this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Author, for though it ſounds like that of the Kentiſh Parſon, who affirmed, that <hi>Tenderdens-ſteepl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was the cauſe of <hi>Goodwins-ſands,</hi> yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> account it as ſolid as any other Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whereby he makes out the point in hand; in truth they are all of the ſame ſtamp.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Whether the Sea doth petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie or no.</note> And whereas he takes check, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſaid they were petrified by the Sea; I ſuſpect no other that pretends <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Philoſophy will deny this property <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> be in the Sea, and I ſhall eaſily allow my Friend to be ſingular. Aſſuredl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:106770:32"/>the Sea does petrifie, by the plenty of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> fixed Salt, any thing that has in it a <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>pideſcent juice;</hi> from whence it is, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at ſo many Stones of various colours <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e caſt up by the Sea. Thus <hi>Coral,</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rwiſe a Plant, is hardened by the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> into a Stone, as Dr. <hi>Jorden</hi> obſerves. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have often ſeen Fiſh-bones caſt up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Sea, which have been almoſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ned into a perfect Stone. Hence it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mes to paſs, that he that has any <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſcent juice,</hi> which Phyſitians uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> call a <hi>Tartarous humor,</hi> ſhall ſooner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ntract the Stone if he eat much Salt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th his meat; and therefore Salt meats <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> found to be very ill for ſuch as are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>clinable to the Stone.</p>
            <p>But while he is managing this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ment, and denying the petrifying <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>operty of the Sea, he ſays, (p. 32.) <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, then what befel</hi> Lot<hi>'s Wife judici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ly,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Of Lot's Wife.</note> 
               <hi>is not ſo great a Miracle as that we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not all naturally turned into Pillars of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>alt, that eat ſo much Sea-ſalt dayly.</hi>— <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere he ſeems to fall into a grand mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ke, while he ſuppoſes that <hi>Lot</hi>'s <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>fe was turned into <hi>Marine</hi> Salt, or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h as we eat with our meat. I do in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106770:33"/>think with Learned Dr. <hi>Rivet,</hi> M. <hi>Cowley</hi> and others, that tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t ſtory of <hi>Lot</hi>'s Wife muſt be li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. Now foraſmuch as we know there is a <hi>Minerâl Salt</hi> which is hard as Stone, and may ſerve ind<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fferently for building, not being ſubject to melt by the moiſture of the Air; it ſeems very probable, that ſhe was turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to that <hi>Mineral Salt,</hi> and not <hi>Marine,</hi> which would have melted with every ſhower, and ſo could not have ſuited with the deſign of God, who would have it to be a durable M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nument of his Indignation againſt her Diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Curioſi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y, contrary to the expreſſed Will of God. O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Salt,</hi> ſee more in <hi>Pliny lib.</hi> 31. <hi>Nat. Hiſt. cap.</hi> 7. And <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſephus</hi> ſayes he ſaw it (<hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Ant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jud. cap.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.) in his dayes, when it had ſtood about o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o years. Although our modern T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>avel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers report there is <hi>nec vola nec veſt gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> now a dayes of it; as both Engl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh, French, Roman and Dutch do teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie. <hi>Vide</hi> Mr. <hi>Geo. Sandys, Pietro del la Valle, Doubdan,</hi> &amp;c. And the Learned Dr. <hi>Iſaac Baſire,</hi> in his Travels in that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106770:33"/>Country, aſſures me, that though he made a diligent enquiry after it, yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> not to be found. But if our Author ſhall ſay, He does not affirm that ſhe was turned into a <hi>Marine</hi> Salt: Why then his mention of it is nothing to the purpoſe!</p>
            <p>As for what he adds concerning the Earth, which in one place turns to an <hi>Ir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n-ſtone,</hi> I have ſaid enough to that p. 28, &amp; 45. of my Anſwer to <hi>Hydrol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ym.</hi> although here he ſeems to infer (for his deſign) that all the earth that f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lls down near the Spaw turns into Stone, which is not ſo.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">arg. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, he endeavors to prove it to be petrifying, <hi>by the effects that it produceth in thoſe that are ſubject to the Stone,</hi> (p. 33.) wherein he cites his own caſe, to wit, <hi>That having been cut f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the S one, and one taken out from his Bladder that weighed four ounces and an half, the Summer following he drank of Knaresb. Spaw, which Water he mixed with white Wine; theſe</hi> (he ſays) <hi>brought <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y by Urine abundance of mucous mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> (p. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>6.)—T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ere he cite<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> a place <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Helmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t,</hi> whom he calls the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106770:34"/>
               <hi>Prince of Reaſon,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>T</hi> cites <hi>Helmont</hi> imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently.</note> who he fancies ſets down the reaſon of that Operation in theſe words: <hi>Ubi cuſtodes male ſe habent, continuo plorant partem pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>prii alimen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> quod ſibi aſſimilare debebat.</hi>— Why he ſhould ſet ſuch an Accent on his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor in his quotation of this Sentence, I know not: The learned Reader will eaſily obſerve what Harmony there is betwixt his Matter for which he cites them; and the Words, for in my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they agree like a Harp and a Harrow. Nor does it appear that he underſtands <hi>Helmont</hi>'s meaning. To ſay no more then what appears true to Learned men, this is one of thoſe Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences wherein <hi>Helmont</hi> affects Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity, and is ſcarce intellig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ble. I ſuſpect my Friend does in this, as 'tis ſaid of ſome Divines, That they <hi>weed</hi> the Fathers works, picking up many times what is impertinent, while they leave the <hi>Flowers</hi> to be plu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>kt by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> 
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scarb.</hi> gave him a fit of the ſtone.</note> Two years after he viſited <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> and brought his Wife and above thirty Perſons of Quality, that lived in and about Newcaſtle, where
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106770:34"/>after a fortnights drinking of that wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, <hi>He ſays it gave him a fit of the Stone, which he had not felt ſince his cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting,</hi> (p. 22) <hi>for he felt it ſlip from the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ft Kidney into his B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>adder,</hi> (p. 43.) <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame inſtant a Thunderbolt from the right Kidney darted into his great Toe; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d afterwards he tells</hi> (p. 33.) <hi>that when be left the Waters, he had another fit for t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> days, and this Stone he will have to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> generated by the Petrifying property of the Spa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> (p. 35.)</p>
            <p>This I have gleaned up out of that confuſed method which he purſues in his Book, the ſubſtance of his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which he groun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s upon his own Experience.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> For Anſwer. Here our Authour <hi>thunders</hi> terribly, and tells of the <hi>bolt</hi> in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e, But where is the <hi>lightning</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll this while? I ſee none, only <hi>light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſs</hi> enough— I do very much won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to find him commending <hi>Knaresb. Spaw</hi> for bringing away the mucous matter, which he acknowledges might have been the Foundation of a Stone, and yet diſcommends <hi>Scarbrough</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>inging down the Stone, Certainly
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106770:35"/>he had the ſame reaſon to charge it as a fault in the former, that it bred the mucous Matter, as in the latter that it bred the Stone, which if he had, no man would have believed it: but I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that would not have ſuited his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign.</p>
            <p>I find him confeſſing (p. 14.) <hi>that Scarb. has imbibed Nitre, which there he acknowledges to be a noble Principle againſt the Stone:</hi> And wherein, I pray, conſiſts the excellency of that Principle, but in expelling the Stone, or diſſolving it? and therefore it is preſcribed by all Phyſitians, antient and modern, for that very purpoſe; and yet here, when he findes it to perform the intention, he ſayes it bred it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I grant</hi> (ſayes he p. 34.) <hi>that by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of abundance of Nitre in the Water, it will force out ſtony gravel in the kidneys when any is there</hi>— Why? is there not reaſon then to ſuſpect, that he that had been wont to have ſtones bred in his body, might have ſo again, for cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly his conſtitution was not altered by the cutting; and ſo this Nitrous Water might bring down what was
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:106770:35"/>bred there before, and not what it ſelf had generated. <hi>Kircher</hi> will tell him, he had reaſon to look for it. <hi>Plures ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctione a calculis liberati tandem eos ite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum concipiunt, eo ferm modo quo Saxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ina evacuatae novos cum tempore conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piunt Saxorum foetus,</hi> lib. 8. ſect. 2. cap. 3. And there alſo he tells him from whence it comes, <hi>viz. à Faculta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis expultricis imbecillitate, &amp; materiae terreſtris &amp; ſalis in humido diluti copia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Again, how can it be ſuppoſed, that while there is ſo conſtant and plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful a current through thoſe paſſages of Urine, and this promoted by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Water, which he confeſſes to be ſo cleanſing, yet at the ſame time a ſtone ſhould be generated, and that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in a fortnights ſpace? Does not he acknowledge (p. 18.) <hi>that he drank it the year before,</hi> and yet we hear nothing of diſlike, but a high commendation of it to many worthy Perſons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity? Indeed then he had another de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to carry on, which if it had ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded, doubtleſs we had heard none of this; but that failing him, as the Pox ſaid in the Fable, the Grapes are
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106770:36"/>ſowr, and <hi>the Nitrous Water breeds the Stone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> Ay but ſome may object to me,<note place="margin">About Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience.</note> you argue againſt <hi>experience,</hi> which is the ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſt Rule to prove a thing; <hi>He tells you, his reins have tried it,</hi> (p. 44.) and found it too true.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer, It had been better if his <hi>brains</hi> had tried it throughly; but ſince we are to ſeek for that, I will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vor in kindneſs to inſtruct him. I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute not againſt <hi>matter of Fact,</hi> but only examine the Inference, Whether that Stone ſo expelled, could be bred by the Spaw or no, and that's a point of <hi>Reaſon.</hi> I am certain he takes <hi>non Cauſam pro Cauſa;</hi> nothing is more ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, then that it was the Cauſe of its Expulſion, but that it ſhould breed it, I have already, and ſhall yet further make it out to be impoſſible.</p>
            <p>A particular mans experience, of <hi>ſuch an One</hi> eſpecially, who for by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ends ſeeks occaſion of cavil, and is glad to finde the leaſt pretence to it may be fallacious, and I am aſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red this is ſo, and in the Judgement of all wiſe Men cannot be ſufficient to be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:106770:36"/>drawn in to make a <hi>Rule to judge</hi> a thing by <hi>Experientia</hi> ſhould be <hi>multiplex;</hi> it muſt be an Induction of a great many particulars, and of long duration, made by impartial and unbyaſſed judgments, that muſt concur to ground a <hi>Rule of Experience</hi> upon.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scarb. Sp.</hi> excellent againſt the ſtone.</note> And I dare undertake to bring in an Induction of hundreds of <hi>honeſt</hi> and <hi>impartial</hi> Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, that can have no ſiniſter deſign at all, who in the Diſeaſe we treat of (to wit, the Stone) have found benefit, and never any the leaſt harm, beſides thoſe I have mentioned in my Book <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alled <hi>Scarb. Spaw Edit.</hi> 2. Let my own Experience come into plea with his, who have frequented it theſe 30. years, beſides ſeveral that I could name, Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Quality, who ſtand admiring at this unreaſonable charge of our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor: Theſe having drunk of it ten or twenty years together and upwards, yet never found the leaſt ill ſymptome from it in this point or any other, when they went regularly to work, and were adviſed.</p>
            <p>I muſt confeſs I have known ſeveral that have got quit of many Stones, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106770:37"/>much Gravel by drinking of it, and ever without any conſiderable pain. I know a Lady that voided 28 <hi>Stones</hi> at theſe Waters, many of them as big as a peaſe, four years ago without trouble. And Mr. <hi>James Duncanſon</hi> a Scotch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, told me the l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſt year he thought he voided half a Jill of Stones and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel at once without much pain, having been very often before ſubject to grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous fits of the Stone. Nothing is plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er every day then this; to finde Stones expelled at theſe Waters; and yet none of theſe, nor I ever had the leaſt ground to ſuſpect that it bred thoſe Stones or Gravel.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A double cauſe of the ſtone.</note> If it bred the Stone in the Body, it muſt do it either as <hi>Cauſa Materialis,</hi> or as <hi>Cauſa Effectrix.</hi> If as a <hi>Material Cauſe,</hi> that muſt be by miniſtring ſome craſs matter which is apt to condenſe into a Stone; but this the water cannot he thought to do, ſince it is a pure wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and that alſo ſtrongly impregnat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with a <hi>Nitrous</hi> Salt, which is a great Diſlolvent, as we have ſaid already, and of thin parts. Secondly, the <hi>Efficient Cauſe</hi> conſiſts in an innate and natural
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106770:37"/>diſpoſition towards the breeding of Stones and Gravel, from the fiery heat of the Reins and circumjacent parts, which condenſes ſome craſs matter into Gravel or a Stone, even as a Pot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters clay is by heat hardened into a ſtone, as <hi>Trallianus</hi> expreſſes it, <hi>lib.</hi> 9. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. now this the water cannot pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote, becauſe it is Nitrous, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently cooling, and is ever found to quench the intemperat heat of the Reins, and all the internal parts.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ob. </seg>
               </label> But our Author accuſes it as a <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial Cauſe,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">About ſtone-ſilings.</note> and to leave matter in the Body which will condenſe into a ſtone, by reaſon of the ſtone-filings that are in it, <hi>p.</hi> 35. where he compares it to the <hi>dropping Well at Knaresb.</hi> that covers any thing that is laid in it ſome while with a ſtony cruſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> To this I reply; the Spring flows as clear as any whatſoever, and if it be clear taken up, as we drink it at the Well, I know no ground of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint. Perhaps in filling of great Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels they may trouble the Spring, and ſo take up ſome gravel or ſand, which might beguile him, and make him
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106770:38"/>look on it as an unſeparable adjunct.</p>
            <p>Again, all waters of this nature that are impregnated with Minerals, will uſually let fall ſomething to the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tom, which is commonly called <hi>Och<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> and this does ſo, whether it be carried in wooden veſſels, or ſtone, or glaſs, though he ſays <hi>p.</hi> 55. <hi>'tis the coroſion of the Veſſels by the Water,</hi> yet learned Writers on the ſubject never thought the worſe of them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Water <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>red.</note> Among the body of Mineral ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dients wherewith this water is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnanted, there is a part after it has paſſed through the heat of the fire in the evaporation of the water, that when it comes to be diſſolved again in pure water, will not paſs the filter, while yet before it came to the fire it would all have paſſed through, as I have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſhewn to ſeveral Perſons of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, when two quarts of the water newly taken out of the Spaw dropped through the filter, and left not ſo much ſand behind, as would make a man wink if it were in his eye, and yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing evaporated away over the fire, it afforded the ſame ſediment in <hi>ſubſtance</hi>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:106770:38"/>and <hi>Quantity,</hi> as if it had not been fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, ſuch alteration has the fire made in it. Now I doubt not but the water which we drink that never came at the fire, whereby the fixed parts of the Minerals ſhould be condenſed, will as eaſily paſs through and penetrate our Bodies, and leave no dregs, as at the firſt it does the filter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Fire a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but not a fit Medium.</note> Indeed I agree with him in this, that fire is the moſt proper inſtrumen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to try what is in the water, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was that I proceeded by it in extracting theſe Minerals, as before I expr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed; but I do not judge it a fit <hi>medium</hi> whereby to prove its working in our Bodies, which is the thing he drives at all along; for that which fire will condenſe or thicken, may yet be as fluid as water in our Bodies. As for example, the <hi>Serum</hi> that is in the Blood, and is its Vehicle to help its Circulation in the Veins and Arteries, is like water, as we ſee it in the veſſels when we take Blood; yet put this into a Saucer, and ſet it on the fire, and immediatly it turns thick like Starch. I knew a worthy Knight in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:106770:39"/>who out of ſome ſuch perſwaſion, was wont to dehort others from drinking of Sack, ſhewing them that a glaſs of Sack poured into a red hot fire-ſhovel, would leave a thick ſediment like <hi>Pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> or Starch, when the thin parts were evaporated; but I ſuppoſe no wiſe Man, or good Fellow, would like it the worſe for that. And therefore upon the whole matter, I may very well and truly deny that any ſuch filings of Stone, or Clay, or Sand are left in our Bodies while we drink this Water, to breed the Stone or any other malady, or the leaſt ill ſymptome; and I am certain, that in the large Experience that I can pretend to in things refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to this Water, there is no ground to believe it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> But that I may yet further diſcover the weakneſs of this Argument, I ſhall let him know, that a water may have a <hi>petrifying</hi> property, ſo as it may turn any thing into a Stone, and yet in a large Tract of Experience, it may be found ſafe to be drunk, yea and be an excellent Remedy againſt the Stone. Did my Friend never read Dr. <hi>Fuller</hi>'s
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106770:39"/>
               <hi>Worthies,</hi> who was a moſt learned and ingenious Gentleman? In his Deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption of <hi>Warwick-ſhire,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 117.) he tells of a Spring at <hi>Newenham Regis</hi> that is ſo p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>trifying, that it turns ſticks into ſtone, (which Mr. <hi>Speed</hi> his Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor whom he cites, ſays he was an Eye-witneſs of) and yet withal he adds, that its found to be very Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rain againſt the Stone. If I were diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, I could tell where our Author has commended the dropping Well to ſome to drink a long time of it, when ſure he had no jealouſie leaſt it ſhould breed the Stone in thoſe Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tients.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> But it appears from this Argument, that <hi>he is of opinion that whatſoever is ſtony, is apt to breed ſtones in the body, and conſequently is dangerous for ſuch as are inclinable to the ſtone.</hi> So he argues (<hi>p.</hi> 32, &amp; 35.) why then how comes it to paſs, that our moſt excellent Writers do preſcribe ſuch things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Stone? <hi>Marcellus</hi> one of the Princes in Phyſick, commends the powder of a Crab-ſhell to be drunk in white Wine againſt the Stone. And
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106770:40"/>
               <hi>Aetius</hi> another, commends that very ſtone that has been bred in the body, and is expelled by urine, to be pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, and drunk as an excellent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy againſt the Stone. (<hi>Petrab.</hi> 3. <hi>ſerm.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 10.) I could multiply in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of like ſort out of our beſt Writers.</p>
            <p>By this reckoning we ſhould lay aſide Pearl, Coral, Crabs eyes, and all ſorts of precious S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ones. We ſhould abandon all our <hi>compound Species</hi> and <hi>Trochisks,</hi> and what not. The <hi>Lady Kents powder</hi> and <hi>Gaſcoigns powder,</hi> with many more, muſt be held dangerous againſt the Stone, and we ſhould uſe nothing but the fiery hot spirits of the <hi>Pſeudochymiſts,</hi> of which we ſhall hear anon. But aſſuredly this doctrine will not eaſily go down with the wiſe Men of this generation, nor will the great Ladies believe it.</p>
            <p>Nothing is more ordinary then to ſee the powder of <hi>Spar,</hi> which is a hard mineral Stone, to be taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly with good ſucceſs, even by wiſe and intelligent perſons, as alſo the powders of Egg ſhells and Gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel-ſeeds,
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106770:40"/>which is almoſt as hard as ſtone, who never can be made to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that they breed the Stone.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>
               </label> But what if ſhould grant him, that the natural heat of the body may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſe the fixed parts of the mineral and metaline Principles of this or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the like waters, as the fire doth, yet it would not follow that they could breed the Stone; for 'tis im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible for ſuch a groſs ſubſtance to paſs through the ſmall and capillar Veins of the Meſentery, or the emul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Veins, which it muſt do before it come into the Kidneys to breed the Stone, nor ever was any ſuch thing found or ſuſpected, till this our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor <hi>fancied</hi> it; but it muſt of neceſſity be thrown by the purging property of the water into the bowels, where no manner of detriment can enſue, and ſo go out by ſiege; nor did ever any thing happen upon the drinking of theſe waters, that could afford any the leaſt ground of jealouſie, that there was any ſuch cauſe, notwithſtanding his pretences.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing our Author is ſo ſevere
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106770:41"/>in his charge againſt it,<note place="margin">A digreſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on about petrifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> as having a <hi>petrifying</hi> property, and thereupon compares it to the <hi>Dropping-well,</hi> I judge it requiſite to make ſome en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiry into the parallel, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider of the cauſes of <hi>petrification</hi> that is in waters, and more particularly that of the <hi>Dropping-well,</hi> how it makes ſtone, and ſo we ſhall the better diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern what ſutableneſs there is in this his parallel; where by the way, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what I ſhall ſay concerning the <hi>nature of ſtone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſtone.</note>It is a point of no ſmall difficulty that I am now fallen upon, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing few that have written of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject unto any competent ſatisfaction. <hi>Fallopius</hi> (<hi>de metallis cap.</hi> 6 found it ſo, and therefore he implored the help of <hi>Marcus Antonius Janna</hi> about it: But at laſt he adventures upon it, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines <hi>Stone to be a mineral ſubſtance con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crete, that is not capable of diſſolution either by heat or moiſture:</hi> And whereas ſome ſtones will diſſolve or melt, he imputes to the mixture of ſome mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral or mettal.— But this is not a full or compleat definition, for as
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106770:41"/>much as we ſee there are ſome ſtones, in which we cannot ſay there is any mineral or mettal, that will neither endure the <hi>fire,</hi> nor yet the <hi>air,</hi> and are therefore accounted improper for building.</p>
            <p>But this is obſervable, that the more pure and fine the matter of any ſtone is, the harder it is, and the more unca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of diſſolution either by heat or moiſture, as <hi>Diamonds, Amethiſts, Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelians,</hi> &amp;c. Nor does it agree with the nature of thoſe ſtones that are bred in the bodies of men, ſome of wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch we find are diſſoluble by the help of theſe waters, though others are not.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration of ſtones.</note>But the cauſe of the generation of ſtones is ſtill more abſtruſe and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult. Some will have them all to be originally nothing but water, but then they ſhould all be pellucid and clear. Some to be only earth condenſed, but then none of them ſhould be pellucid. Beſides, why ſhould any of them be heavier then earth, ſince they are drier; for we ſee the ſame piece of earth when 'tis dry, is far lighter then
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:106770:42"/>when 'tis moiſt, unleſs we ſhall attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute it to its more cloſe and compact ſubſtance, which is not enough.</p>
            <p>The beſt account we can give, is that every ſort of ſtone has its <hi>Succus Lapideſcens</hi> (as mettals have) before it be concrete, and that concretion is furthered ſometimes by <hi>cold,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times by <hi>heat.</hi> Thus by <hi>cold,</hi> thoſe Springs that have imbibed any ſort of Lapideſcent juyce, may petrifie or make a ſtone of the ſame kind, and the ſooner if there be any mixture of a <hi>fixed ſalt</hi> in it, and the water be kept from motion. By the other (to wit) <hi>heat,</hi> may any craſſe matter be turned into a ſtone; as the clay in a Potters furnace, is by the fiery heat condenſed into a ſtone.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Stones of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten found in the body.</note>There are alſo ſtones generated in the concave parts of mens bodies ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry frequently, by the immoderate heat of the parts condenſing craſſe matter, as in the Gall, the Reins, the Bladder, the Stomach, the Womb, as have been found in d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſections frequently; ſo likewiſe in the very Arteries and Veins. <hi>Kircher</hi> tells, that he was pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:106770:42"/>when <hi>Joannes Trulla</hi> a Chirur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon found many ſtones, and much urtarous matter in the <hi>great Artery,</hi> near to its union with <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>na Cava,</hi> in one <hi>Barthelinus Cenventinus,</hi> which ſtopped the motion of the blood and ſpirits, and brought ſudden death. The like was found lately in the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ry of a <hi>Noble Peer</hi> of this Realm, which rendred his diſeaſe incurable, as I had a relation from my Friend Dr. <hi>Troutbeck,</hi> who was preſent at the diſſection. Many ſtories of like ſort may be found in <hi>Schenkin</hi>'s <hi>Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionss,</hi> as alſo in <hi>Laurentius</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtoria Anatomica.</hi> Yea and ſometimes ſtones have been found in the <hi>ſolid and muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulous parts.</hi> I have ſeen a ſtone as hard as a flint, and in all reſpects like one, as one flint can be like another, that after much pain in the part and of long duration, was cut out of a mans buttock at <hi>Doncaſter,</hi> which would ſtrike fire upon ſteel.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Springs that have imbibed ſtones.</note>I read in good Authors of ſeveral Springs that are impregnated with ſtone, as the <hi>Aqua Aponitana</hi> which <hi>Fallopius</hi> ſays has Limeſtone, as alſo
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:106770:43" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Baths of <hi>Eugeſta</hi> according to <hi>Geſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> and that at <hi>Corſena</hi> has ſhreds of Marble. So at <hi>Giret</hi> near <hi>Vienna</hi> in <hi>Savoy</hi> there is a Spring whoſe water petrifies into flints. This muſt neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily from the diverſity of the Lapideſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent juyces which thoſe Springs have imbibed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A rare Spring in <hi>France.</hi>
               </note>But the moſt ſtupendious is a Spring at <hi>Clarmont</hi> in <hi>Averne,</hi> a Province in <hi>France,</hi> which though it flows as limpid and clear as any other water, yet it turns all its ſubſtance in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſtone, if it be ſuffered to ſtand ſtill in any veſſel; and being put into a glaſs of what ſhape you pleaſe, it will turn preſently into a ſtone of the ſame form. <hi>Petrus Joannes Faber</hi> a French Phyſitian, in his <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drographum Spagyricum</hi> (<hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 14.) reports of this water that they are wont to make Bridges of it to paſs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Gardens, over the Rivulet that comes from it, by placing timber, and then pumping up the water upon it, they have a compleat ſtone-bridge in 24. hours. This water he ſays kills any beaſt that drinks of it, for as much as it turns into a ſtone in the ſtomach—
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:106770:43"/>The ſaid Author undertakes to give a reaſon for i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, (to wit) <hi>That the</hi> Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritus Mundi <hi>with a peculiar influence of the Stars upon this Spring more then any other, does excite the aſtringent and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agulating property that is in the Sal, one of the three Chymical principles, whereby the water upon r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſting, or ceaſing of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, ſhall convert into a ſtone.</hi> But in my judgement, he had as good have ſaid nothing, for ſo he may eaſily ſolve all the <hi>Phaenomena</hi> in Nature, be they never ſo difficult, which have puzled all the <hi>Sages</hi> of the World, by attributing them to the activity of the <hi>Spiritus Mundi,</hi> and the Stars in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences upon one or more of their three principles, to wit, <hi>Sal, Sulphur,</hi> and <hi>Mercury.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But in all probability; the true cauſe muſt be this, that this whole matter that runs out of the Spring, is a <hi>Lapideſcent juyce,</hi> and not water, which when it ceaſes to move, as it does in the Spring or Rivulet, imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately it hardens into a ſtone. For motion hinders the concretion, as we ſee in water, which in the coldeſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:106770:44"/>weather never frezes while 'tis kept in motion, but let it reſt, and then it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verts to ice.</p>
            <p>And ſo I may ſay of our petrifying Springs, which only differ in <hi>magis</hi> and <hi>minus,</hi> ſeveral of which I have ſeen in this County of <hi>York,</hi> which do cover a ſtick, ſtraw, or moſs with a ſtony cruſt, and theſe of ſeveral co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours, according to the nature and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of that ſort of <hi>Lapideſcent juyce,</hi> which the water hath imbibed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the Dropping-Well.</note>But the moſt famous of them all, and moſt petrifying by far of any that this Kingdom affords, is the <hi>Dropping-Well</hi> at <hi>Knaresbrough;</hi> it is a Spring that bubbles out of the Earth in a Meadow Cloſe, near adjoyning to the River of <hi>Nid,</hi> that runs under the Walls of the Town, belonging to Sir <hi>Thomas Slingsby:</hi> It is as clear as any other Spring-water, and the Cattle drink of it. After thirty or forty yards from the Spring, it runs by a very ſmall channel into a ſpungy porous Rock, about twelve yards long, which hangs upon the edge of another ſtony Rock, (all the earth thereabouts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:106770:44"/>rocky) there it diffuſes it ſelf, and continually diſtils through the pores of the ſpungy Rock, like a plentiful rain, into the ground that is under it, much lower then the Meadow. That ground into which it drops, is all be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a ſolid Rock, wherein if a ſtick or moſs be ſuffered to lie ſome while, it covers it with a ſtony cruſt, and in time converts it into a ſtone, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like <hi>Lime-ſtone,</hi> but clearer and ſmother; from thence it runs into the River of <hi>Nid,</hi> which is within a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en yards of it, where the Spring-water has made a Rock, that ſtretches ſome yards into the River.</p>
            <p>There are no ſymboles of any <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trifying</hi> property in the Spring or Stream that runs from it, upon ſtraws or moſs, till it comes into the Rock; which to my apprehenſion ſeems to be made by the petrification which the water at the beginning might receive from the Rock upon which it hangs, from which it might derive a <hi>Lapideſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent juyce,</hi> and doubtleſs it is now emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently exalted in its coldneſs from the <hi>ſpungy Rock,</hi> for it is a very cold water
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:106770:45"/>which quality meeting with the <hi>Lapi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſcent juyce,</hi> and a ſmall proportion of a <hi>fixed Salt,</hi> doth produce the petrify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing property.</p>
            <p>This water is in eſteem for ſtaying of <hi>inveterate Fluxes</hi> of the belly, of which they uſe to drink a long time together without any harm at all; and I have ſometimes obſerved, without any benefit as to the ſtaying of the <hi>Flux.</hi> If it be evaporated away, it leaves in the bottom of the veſſel a very ſharp and gretty ſtone-powder, ſomewhat ſalt and brackiſh, for the fire fixes the <hi>Lapideſcent juyce.</hi> Our Author calls it <hi>Nitre,</hi> following there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Kircher;</hi> but I have proved it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready to be inconſiſtent with the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and property of <hi>Nitre</hi> to make a ſtone. Nor does that <hi>ſalt,</hi> which is found in the ſediment of the <hi>Dropping-Well,</hi> ſhoot into <hi>ſtiria's,</hi> as the <hi>Nitre</hi> does at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and wherever elſe it has been found.— Now it being plain, and that by his own confeſſion, that <hi>Scarb. Spaw</hi> has in it abundance of <hi>Nitre,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 34.) it is impoſſible it ſhould be <hi>petrifying,</hi> or make a ſtone.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:106770:45"/>And ſince 'tis alſo manifeſt, that the <hi>Dropping Well</hi> has <hi>no Nitre</hi> in it, it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows that the parallel is <hi>naught and frivolous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A rare caſe of help in the ſtone.</note>To ſum up all in a few words: while Doctor <hi>Tonſtall</hi> has deſigned to charge it on the Spaw, that it <hi>breeds</hi> the ſtone in the kidneys and bladder, he has in truth proved by an inſtance drawn from himſelf, tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> it is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent water againſt the Stone, foraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>much as when he knew not from any foregoing ſymptomes, that he had any ſtones in his kidneys, ſave only that he had formerly been cut for the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>one, and his private conſtitution might again incline him to it: It did not only like a light brought into a dark r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om, diſcover a lurking Thief, (as I had occaſion to expreſs it elſe where) to wit, a Stone and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſpace of <hi>one fortnight,</hi> but had alſo ſo much power and efficacy as to expel it, and alſo to ſet nature on work ſome weeks after, to clear it ſelf of the ſtones and gravel which it had diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodged, which if they had been retent within the body, would undoubtedly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:106770:46"/>have increaſed to a greater bulk, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps in a little more time impoſſible to be expelled, and ſo have drawn him into a neceſſity of another cutting.</p>
            <p>I have been the longer in this Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, both becauſe in this he ſeems herein to be moſt earneſt, often pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting in choler enough, on purpoſe to gain Proſelytes and beget belief (though I think there are but few to be found, that will judge the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flowing of his Gill, to add any force to his Argument) and becauſe ſome others even of <hi>eminent Quality</hi> of my Friends, whom I <hi>very much</hi> honour, had ſome ſuch jealouſie, upon this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ground, that they never diſcovered that they had the ſymptomes of the Stone, till this Water found it out, and expelled both ſtones and gravel; while yet ſcarce any of that Family have been free from the Stone, that lived to any competent years: And further, becauſe on this <hi>Hypotheſis, Hang</hi> all the reſt of the Arguments of accuſation which he brings againſt the water.</p>
            <p>What need I ſay any more in p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:106770:46"/>of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> to convince wiſe men of the ungroundedneſs of this his charge; I ſhall add a little more in point of <hi>experience,</hi> that I have lately met with very many intelligent Perſons, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving had large experience of the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit by this water in the Stone, either in themſelves or their relations, have read this his charge with ſome indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, and have willingly effered their teſtimony. Ile mention but two for brevity.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>John Beaumont</hi> of <hi>Frankfeſſe</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Another</note> his Wife had been very many years ſubject to <hi>grievous fits of the Stone,</hi> for which ſhe had taken much advice, though with little ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; ſhe went afterwards to <hi>Knareſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi> and drank thoſe waters, but found no benefit; then her Husband brought her to <hi>Scarb.</hi> which water brought away the matter of Stone in Gravel and Sand to a great proportion, even in <hi>one weeks</hi> time, ſince when (being now five years) ſhe has had no neceſſity of returning to the Spaw, being free of all ſymptome<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. — Himſelf alſo very much ſubject to <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pochondriack
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:106770:47"/>Wind,</hi> which much diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his head with ſtrange fantaſies, finds perfect cure by theſe waters, having frequented them now theſe twelve years, and ſo reſolves to continue while God ſpares life, being aged ſixty and five.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Another ſpecial Caſe.</note>The other is the Experience of Mr. <hi>George Waugh</hi> of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> a neighbor of Dr. <hi>Tonſtals,</hi> expreſſed in his letter to me.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <p>Sir, <hi>I judge my ſelf obliged to give my teſtimony of the Spaw, and its good effects in my caſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. And fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſt, I bleſs God that he has afforded me ſo great help by it; and alſo I let you know, that it proved eff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ctual almoſt beyond my firſt belief of the water, even to my admiration. In the year</hi> 1669. <hi>at my firſt viſiting of the Well, the water did not onely bring away a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d ſtone, as large as any Date-ſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ne, with its bed in which it lay, but as I found did alſo ſoften and diſſolve what was more in my Body, ſo that at one Urine</hi> (as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member) <hi>I voided above a dozen ſtones, moſt of them as large as a white peaſe, which did lie in the baſon as ſtones; but I draining the water off, and thinking to take
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:106770:47"/>them up, they would not bear their own weight, but betwixt my fingers became ſand, and theſe I voided the very day I left the Spaw. At my return in</hi> 1670. <hi>I had not arunk eight pints of the water the firſt morning, until a large quantity of the tartarous tough matter that breeds the ſtone came away, which I know was cauſed by the vertue of the Water.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I am your, &amp;c. <hi>GEORGE WAUGH.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>Here I think fit to inſert a ſtory that I have heard from a Gentleman of Quality who aſſerts the truth of it. A Gentleman that was ſorely afflicted with the Stone of the Bladder, was cut for it, and a ſtone of great bigneſs was taken out, his Friend begged it of him, and made a knife-haft of it; as he was ſitting at dinner one day with other Friends, they held long in diſcourſe, while his knife laid ſtill up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his trencher, which when he took up, he found the haft to have a dimple in it on one ſide, and obſerving, he
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:106770:48"/>judged it to have proceeded from a Radiſh upon which the haſt had laid, which had diſſolved it: this gave oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to another Gentleman, who was wont to be ſeverely tormented with the Stone, to eat Radiſhes much, which he found to diſſolve the Stone in his Bladder, and bring it away in abundance of Gravel and Sand, ſo as he was afterwards freed from his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> But I muſt look back to (<hi>p.</hi> 15.) where our Author tells a ſtory of Mr. <hi>Stone</hi>'s Son, (its the Printers miſtake, for it ſhould be Mr. <hi>Stow</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Newton upon Trent</hi> in <hi>Nottingham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire</hi> how that the Spaw at <hi>Knaresb.</hi> hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped towards the healing of his wound in the neck of the Bladder, after he had been cut for the Stone, for which great cure (ſayes our Author) he did frequent that Spaw many yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. — Ile go on with the ſtory<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> this Gentlemen and his Son having heard of the fame of <hi>Scarb. Spaw,</hi> did about eight or nine years ago make a journey thither, in which water they found ſo much more real benefit in
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:106770:48"/>that diſeaſe of the Stone then they had before, that to this day they never returned to <hi>Knaresb.</hi> but have been conſtant drinkers of <hi>Scarb.</hi> waters, either going thither, or elſe ſending for the water to <hi>Newton,</hi> though it be near thirty miles further diſtant then the other.</p>
            <p>Another ſtory he tells (<hi>p.</hi> 35.) of one that was brought very low in a <hi>Hectick Peaver,</hi> and ſadly troubled with a ſhortneſs of breath, but found no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy till drinking of <hi>Knaresb. Spaw</hi> he coughed up ſtones every day. If this Patient (ſayes he) had been ſent to <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> what had become of him? — I dare ſay he knows not, for it well appears he does not under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand that water, either through defect of opportunities of obſervation, or from a judgement ſwayed aſide by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, or blinded by intereſt. But it is not my diſpoſition now to make a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon betwixt theſe two waters: Let them agree till they meet ſay I, and then if they fall out, I know which is the <hi>nimbler,</hi> and <hi>better mettal'd</hi> too. But our Author ſhould have done well
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:106770:49"/>to have informed himſelf what inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the Doctor deſigned, that in a difficulty of breathing he ſhould adviſe him to drink that water, and whether he knew there were any ſtones in his Lungs, and could expect that the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſhould help their expectoration, or whether it was not rather ſome ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidental cure that he expected not. He ſhould alſo have told us what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt quality there is in that water to promote the coughing up of ſtones, more then there is in <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and whether it was expected to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by ſome occult quality: And whether or no a miſtaken fantaſie in Dr. <hi>T.</hi> will hereafter prove a real im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pediment in <hi>Scarb. Spaw</hi> for the doing of cures.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of clay and ſand in the Spaw.</note>But I may not pretermit that <hi>he accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes this water to have ſand and clay in it, whereby it hurts feeble ſtomachs, and be undertakes</hi> (p. 23.) <hi>to tell what proportion there is of it in the water.</hi>— This has been in part anſwered already, while we were diſcourſing about the <hi>ſtone particles,</hi> wherein he placed the <hi>petri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying</hi> property. We have ſaid before,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:106770:49"/>that the fire does condenſe ſome fixed parts of the mineral and metalline ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, or the Earth through which it paſſes, yet exceeding ſhort of that proportion that he mentions, nor in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed is it worth enquiry, ſince never my harm came by it, be it more or leſs, theſe thirty years to my know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that might be reaſonably aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to any ſuch cauſe. But let us exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine it firſt in Reaſon, and then we will come to Experience.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">All ſorts of water have ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</note>This is certain, that the moſt pure ſimple water in all the world, being tor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fied in the fire, as we do in extracting the minerals out of this water, will be found to have ſand and other earthy matter in it, as Mr. <hi>Boyle</hi> has made out: For he ſayes, take the pureſt and moſt common Spring-water, and diſtil it in the pureſt <hi>glaſs retort</hi> an hundred times over, and there ſhall ever) time be found a quantity of ſand as a bottom ſediment.<note place="margin">Eſpecially Mineral-waters.</note> But this is more eſpecially true in Mineral-wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and ſtill more in ſuch of them as have imbibed Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral-juyces, whether they be hot or cold Springs, &amp; never till now did any<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:106770:50"/>man of Art eſteem them the worſe for it: Such as that at <hi>Bourbon</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the minerals whereof have been ſhewn me by the Noble <hi>Lord Falconberge,</hi> and yet by the Advice of all the Phyſitians that water is taken inwardly, as alſo our own at <hi>Bathe.</hi> So the <hi>Acque Ace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſe</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> the <hi>Pouhout</hi> and <hi>Sauvenir</hi> in <hi>Germany, Epſam, Tunbridge, Barnet, Aſtrap, Ieatham,</hi> yea and that of <hi>Kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resb.</hi> upon my own knowledge, which upon the evapora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion of the water, (as I do at <hi>Scarb.</hi>) yields a great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion of clay and ſand (as he calls it) and ſcarce any thing elſe. Yea Dr. <hi>French</hi> in his Book of that water con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſes it.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Note. </seg>
               </label> He refer him to a Chymiſt, who will tell him this is common to other Springs of this ſort. <hi>Petrus Johannes Faber</hi> in his <hi>Hydrogr. Spagyr.</hi> (<hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 16.) treating of Mineral-water, and wherein conſiſts their vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, has theſe words.— <hi>Nam diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latis aquis quacunque Arte ex nonnullis Fontibus infinitarum quaſi vir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utum, ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil repertum eſt in fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>do diſtill<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nis, praterquam Limus, &amp; Terra quaed<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:106770:50"/>craſſa &amp; faeculenta nullius virtutis &amp; ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficaciae</hi> &amp;c. (to wit) by what Art ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever the Waters of ſome ſprings be diſtilled, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch are yet of infinite ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, nothing is to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd in the bot<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>om but mud, and ſome groſs and earthy dregs of no vertue, and efficacy a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>l. And thus I am certain it is with <hi>Kn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resb.</hi> which this year he ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ols ſo much, and which either our Author has not obſerved, or out of deſign is not wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to acknowledge.</p>
            <p>And therefore either he did not ☜ know this when he writ this Book, or he did. If he had not known it, then it betokens <hi>ignorance</hi> in a conſiderable point of Philoſophy, and in that part wherein he ought eſpecially to have been better inſtructed.— If he did know it, and yet goes about to buz it into the heads of the vulgar as a pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar fault of <hi>Scar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rough,</hi> it ſavours ſtill worſe, he might as well accuſe any of them as this; nay upon this <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> no water in the world ſhould be wholſome to be drunk, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the <hi>ſand or gravel</hi> that is in it, which <hi>fire</hi> diſcovers. Although for any
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:106770:51"/>man to repine at it, were doubtleſs an Atheiſtical preſumption, and a grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous ſin againſt <hi>God,</hi> who has ſo order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in his infinite wiſedom, while either its not worſe for our bodies, or if it be, it depends upon his Will, who not only in his Statute and Decree has de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined us all to be ſubject to death, but alſo in his wiſe proviſion of things moſt neceſſary for our being, will gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dually diſpoſe our bodies to a ſtate of mutation and corrptibility.</p>
            <p>What could our Author expect (I wonder) to find the element of water?<note place="margin">No ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of water to be found,</note> Surely no: all Fountains are mixed bodies made up of the four elements, and in reſpect of the earth which is the <hi>matrix</hi> within which they are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated, and to which they are ſo nearly united, they partake largely of a terreſtrial matter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scarb. Spaw</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent for a feeble ſtomach.</note> I do ſeriouſly profeſs, I could never obſerve any the leaſt harm to feeble Stomachs, but have always found it highly to ſharpen the <hi>appetite,</hi> and alſo further the <hi>concoction.</hi> Nay I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain there is not in Nature a more ſpeedy Remedy for a debilitated Sto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach.
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:106770:51"/>Never did any feeble Stomach (if that was the main fault) return from theſe waters without eminent good ſucceſs, when they were regular and would be adviſed. My <hi>Lord of Suffolk</hi>'s ſtupendious cure which I mention (<hi>p.</hi> 174. of <hi>Scarb. Sp. Edit.</hi> 2.) confirms this, with others that are there recited. Nor if you mind, does he bring any inſtance to confirm this charge, but as in the former indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment about its breeding the Stone, he has no witneſs but himſelf, nor one plauſible argument to prove it; ſo here he ſtands alone to make good this accuſation againſt that cloud of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes which I have produced, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though I am certainly informed from ſome that know full well, he did earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtly endeavor to procure ſome to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt them both, but was ſeverely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected.</p>
            <p>I have know ſome Perſons of qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, who when they came, could not ſit down at the Ordinaries with others, leſt they ſhould give offence by their <hi>con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inual belching,</hi> which always ſeiſed on them at meat, who found a perfect
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:106770:52"/>cure by the waters, and ſome additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal helps which I thought fit. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may confidently ſay, I have know many ſcores that through debility of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive faculty of the Stomach, were wont to <hi>puke</hi> up their meat before it was half concocted, that have found cures, even when all other means have failed, and when they have been ſuppoſed to be far in <hi>conſumptions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A rare cure.</note>Major <hi>Samuel Taylor</hi> a Gentleman wel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> known to our Superiors, and the <hi>high<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt Grandees</hi> of the Kingdom, by a Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſion he has from his <hi>Majeſty</hi> for the making of the Mould at <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger,</hi> was about n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een years ago ſo low brought with a lingring weakneſs, attended with a conſtant Cough, and ioſs of appetite, that his legs could ſcarce bear him, and was wholly given up by all as in a Conſumption, found here a perfect cure in a very ſhort time. The two or three laſt years finding at <hi>Tanger</hi> the old ſymptomes returning, which brought him ſo weak that he could not attend his employment but on h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſeback, he obtaind leave to come for <hi>England</hi> purpoſely to drink theſe
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:106770:52"/>waters at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> wherein by the way (eſpecially at <hi>London</hi>) he met with ſufficient diſcouragements from many (otherwiſe knowing) perſons, fearing the waters would kill him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> grounding their jealouſies upon this Book of D. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nſtal,</hi> but his former experience had fixed his reſolution, ſo as the laſt Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer (<hi>viz.</hi> 1670.) he came to <hi>Scarb.</hi> and ſtaid about three weeks, then af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a few weeks reſpit and receſs he come again, and ſtaid nine or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ten days at the waters, and was reduced (God be praiſed) to his perfect health, ſtrength and ſtomach, as ever he had in all his life.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">An ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal.</note>I appeal to all the Lords, Ladies, Gentlemen, and others that were ever adviſed by me at theſe waters at <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough,</hi> for I cannot juſtifie the drink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them abroad, when perhaps it may be adulterated by the Carriers, or elſe become putrid, whether they have not found their ſtomachs advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by it, both in point of appetite and digeſtion. Our Landlords tables in <hi>Scarb.</hi> finde we want not ſtomacks, where we feed like <hi>Farmers,</hi> and are
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:106770:53"/>heartily merry, year and he himſelf in the two Summers that he viſited the waters, know it to be true.</p>
            <p>Its very uſual for many to come in various caſes on their own accords, and ſo drink largely and boldly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any advice firſt had, or direction in drinking, and they think all is well becauſe the water paſſes freely with them, if ſuch return without ſucceſs or get harm, where is the fault? Poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly our Author may have met with ſome of theſe, which he could not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs, though perhaps another might; muſt it needs be charged upon the water or its principles?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Several Indict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments againſt <hi>Scr. Sp.</hi> anſwered.</note>He is indeed very forward in his Accuſation, and in this very point he confeſſes (<hi>p.</hi> 21) he preferred an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment againſt the Water before the <hi>Lord Falconberge</hi> about the <hi>ſandy faeces,</hi> while yet <hi>he acknowledges he was not cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, but that much of it came by the careleſneſs of the Porter that brought him the water.</hi>— I could reply to the purpoſe if I were diſpoſed, but I know my limits. Sure. I am that <hi>noble Lord</hi> is ſo well knowing, and throughly ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:106770:53"/>with the <hi>innocency</hi> and <hi>excellency</hi> of this water, that no man can impoſe upon him, nor will his Lordſhip own any thing that tends to its diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>But there is yet another fault which he fancies to enſue from the <hi>ſand</hi> and <hi>clay</hi> that he has told of, and the <hi>ſtone faeces,</hi> (to wit) that <hi>they are plaſtered upon the inner coat of the bowels, diſturb the periſtaltick motion, and obſtruct the attraction of the lacteal veins.</hi> — Hard words indeed, enough to fright chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, but they that are wiſe will not be ſtartled at Bugbears. <hi>Poſito uno ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdo mille ſequuntur;</hi> the cauſe and the effect are much alike. The truth is, 'tis nothing more then a frivolous conceit, and not worthy to be repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to.</p>
            <p>But this effect of the ſand becomes a cauſe of ſtill furthers miſchief, (to wit) that <hi>after you have drunk a month with ſucceſs, it takes a teſty jadiſh fit, and will neither go backward nor forward,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 25.) and ſayes he, (<hi>p.</hi> 26.) <hi>Is this the manner of other waters?</hi> — Yes, I can tell him, that <hi>Knaresb.</hi> water
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:106770:54"/>will not go through at any time in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary bodies,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Scarbr.</hi> compared with <hi>Kua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resb.</hi>
               </note> unleſs it be either drawn or driven; and ſhall I ſay it is from the ſandy ſediment which I found upon evaporation? Surely no, but for want of another thing which he calls the <hi>eſſence of a Spaw,</hi> which ſhould carry it through. But I am not quarrelſome againſt that water. He had told his friends the laſt year when he invited them to come to <hi>Scarbr.</hi> that it was a nimble and well working water, and if he could have brought about his deſign, it would ſo have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued this year.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Compared with the German.</note>I am certain no water in the world that I read of, is leſs guilty of this fault then <hi>Scarb.</hi> nay let them find me ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that will paſs a month together with like ſucceſs. I am certain the <hi>German</hi> come far ſhort of it, for as Dr. <hi>Heer</hi> confeſſes in his <hi>Spadacrene,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 122.) they have ſcarce one ſtool in eight days that drink of it, even ſuch as were wont to retrograde once eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day at home. But it after ſo well working there happen to be any ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, muſt the fault needs be in
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:106770:54"/>the water? Is it not poſſible that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture may be weary after a month, and ſo become a <hi>ſlug?</hi> Or may it not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from ſome accidental thing in the Patient? Do we not ſee freequently that the ſame doſe of Diet-drink which we preſcribe, comes ſometimes far ſhort of what it operates at another day, and if ſo, where is the alteration but in the body?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Accidents at all wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</note>Its very ordinary for accidents to happen at all theſe waters, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is need of Phyſitians that underſtand them, and know how to correct them, although as rarely at <hi>Scarb.</hi> as at any other in the world. As for the <hi>Lord</hi> he mentions, in whom it ſtopt after a months well working, I know whom he means; that <hi>Lord</hi> told me he could never get quit of him, till at length he yielded to take ſomething of him; and I profeſs ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly, his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> told me, he found no manner of alteration: So I gave him ſomewhat to take off the waters, and he returned home with benefit, having come above two hundered miles.</p>
            <pb n="76" facs="tcp:106770:55"/>
            <p>The truth is, its againſt my will for any one to drink this water a whole month together, but rather I adviſe to a little intermiſſion, and then go to it again, if the work be not done.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>T.</hi> wreſts the Authors ſenſe.</note>But he ſeems to confirm this aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from my own expreſſions in my Book, as you may ſee in his twenty ſixth page— Thus where I am lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down cautions about orderly and regular drinking, that no man hurt himſelf through want of a Rule, he converts them to arguments againſt the water, as is obſervable throughout his whole diſcourſe. Do not all Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors that treat of ſuch ſubjects, lay down rules and give cautions for or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly drinking of the waters they treat of? As Dr. <hi>Heers</hi> and others of the <hi>German,</hi> Dr. <hi>Dean</hi> and Dr. <hi>French</hi> of <hi>Knaresbrough,</hi> Dr. <hi>Rooſy</hi> of <hi>Tunbridg, &amp;c.</hi> and muſt all theſe be wreſted to a contrary ſenſe, as that they imply ſome faults in their waters; certainly nothing can be more diſingenious. Sure I am none of theſe ever met with ſuch contradiction, and wreſting of
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:106770:55"/>their ſenſe as I have done. But I allow every man his humour, though it coſts me ſome Trouble, provided the end may be good, as here it will. — I now proceed.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of Spaws.</note>He ſayes in his Preface, <hi>that the Eſſence of Scarb. Spaw is fit for the Cup of a Prince, but the</hi> Caput Mortuum, <hi>which is that he calls the Stonefillings, Clay and Sand, is for nothing but the Brick-Layers Trowel.</hi>—Tis well there is any any thing in it that is good. — Now by the <hi>Eſſence</hi> he means the refined parts (to wit) the Mineral Salts, which are extracted by force of Fire. But I wonder why the groſſer of fixed parts ſhould be excluded from being <hi>Eſſential</hi> to the Water, any more then the Body, which is of a groſſer ſubſtance then the Soul ſhould be excluded from being the <hi>Eſſential</hi> part of a Man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Sca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>br. compared with Knaresb.</note>If the Salt be the only <hi>Eſſence,</hi> then it will follow that <hi>Knaresb.</hi> Water which <hi>this year</hi> he magnifies ſo much, has little or <hi>no Eſſence,</hi> for in the Evaporation of 10. Gallons, I had a great quantity of <hi>Clay and Sand,</hi> as I
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:106770:56"/>ſaid before, and but 17. Grins of Salt, 3. pints of <hi>Scarb. Water</hi> affording as much: So the conſequent muſt b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> that there is nothing n <hi>Knaresb.</hi> Spaw fit for a Prince, ſince it has little or nothing of Eſſence.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The the Volatile ſpirits.</note>But the truth is, there is yet ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing that is <hi>Eſſential</hi> to all theſe ſorts of Waters, and that is their <hi>Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latile parts</hi> which being <hi>Aetherial</hi> do eaſily van<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh by the innate heat of Fountaines even without Fire, and canot be catched by any Project of Art, and their conſiſts much of their Virtue, although their purging pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty lyes mainly in their S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lts. and much of their Deoppila<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing too: And if it were not for this <hi>Knaresb. Spaw</hi> were not worth a Ruſh, while yet we know it wants not Virtue, although it rarely paſſes by Siege, only by V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine, which ſo much whey would do, or common Water, although not with that Benefit. And hence it is as I am certainly informed from ſome that know it full well, that he himſelf ſends for <hi>Scarb.</hi> Water to <hi>Newc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtle,</hi> out of which he extracts that which
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:106770:56"/>he calls the <hi>Eſſence,</hi> and gives it with <hi>Knaresb.</hi> Water (even at <hi>Knares<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough</hi>) as a great Secret, which o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Phiſicians there muſt not know, on purpoſe to further its Operation.</p>
            <p>But as for thoſe groſs Parts which after Evaporation will not paſs the Filter, and are common to all Mine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Waters (as I ſaid before), they are for the moſt part nothing elſe then the Fixed parts of theſe Mineralls or Metalls which the fire condenſes, though in our Bodies they are not Diſcoverable, and are of ſingular uſe for the making of the Waters more ſafe for inward Uſes and ends, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducing to the fortifying of the Natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Parts. For if the piercing Salts were in the Water alone, they would open the Obſtructions of the Liver and Meſentery very well, but then they would go nere to ſpoil the Tone of the Liver, by purging and attenuating too much, but having the Virtue of the groſs and fixed parts, there is joyned an Aſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iction, by which the Natural Parts are ſtrengthened,<note place="margin">Scarb. For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifies the Liver, &amp;c.</note> and the Tone of the Liver preſerved, beſides that it
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:106770:57"/>ſecures the Body from running into fluxes; And from hence alſo comes it, that though it be an aperient Water, yet it ſtayes the immoderate Fluxes of women.</p>
            <p>And this that I ſay is according to the Doctrine of <hi>Galen,</hi> who <hi>(lib. de Curand. Morb. Cap. De Hep. affect.)</hi> adviſes that in all <hi>Hepatick</hi> Medicines, ſome things be added which are <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derately</hi> Aſtringent, otherwiſe Apperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, Piercing and Purging Medicines will undoubtedly debiliate it. And to this agree all our beſt Writers, and we finde it true in our Practiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Another charge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Jaundice.</note>Another grand Indictment that he prefers againſt <hi>Scarb. Spaw</hi> is, that <hi>it is Obſtructive and cauſes the Jaundice, for proof whereof he cites the Lord E's. Caſe,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 37.) This is the Caſe I glance at, (<hi>p.</hi> 149) of <hi>Scarb. Spaw Edit</hi> 2.) in dark Language having no mind to have it publiquely known whom I meant. <hi>Dr. T.</hi> aſked me again and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with very much importunity one day laſt year at <hi>Scar.</hi> in great Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, at leaſt pretended, whoſe Caſe it was; If I was prevailed withall by his
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:106770:57"/>ſoothing words to tell him privately, being a Brother of the Facultie, &amp;c. He did unworthily to tell it to the World, ſo as to charge it as a Fault in a P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rſon of ſuch Honour in hurting himſelf with drinking wine. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; ☜ What pump me, and then tell abroad my <hi>ſecret?</hi> the very School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boys will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ame him for this, and are better taught, <hi>Nec retinent patulae com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſa, &amp;c.</hi> This is not done like a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian, but— This brings to my mind a ſtory in <hi>Plutarch (de Curioſitate)</hi> of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n <hi>Egyptian</hi> that was carrying ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in a Basket covered. One came to him, and asked what it was that he had covered ſo cloſe. <hi>Ideo (inquit) ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lutum eſt. Tu verò cur curiose veſtigas quod occultatum eſt? Si nihil eſſet mali non fuiſſet occultatum:</hi> (to wit) It is therefore hid that thou mayſt not cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly enquire what it is. Had there been no evil in it, it ſhould not have been hid. I muſt confeſs, this frets me more then all his Book beſide. Ile
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:106770:58"/>only add one Advice to every ingenious Reader upon this occaſion, which I have out of <hi>Publius Cyrus, vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Ita Amicum h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>beas poſſe ut furi hunc I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micum putes.</hi>— So treat your Friend, as if you ſhould ſuſpect he might in time become an Enemy.</p>
            <p>He ſayes <hi>the wat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> brought his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip into the Jaundic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> that killed him, p.</hi> 37. I do ſeriouſly profeſs <hi>my Lord</hi> was in a decaying condition by a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xy,</hi> and alſo ſick when h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> came to <hi>Scarb.</hi> and more fit for his Bed then a Journey of ſixty miles. His <hi>Lordſhip</hi> drank but three quarts in a whole week, and that altogether againſt my will and adv ce, and that at twice, (to wit) three pints at a time, and with two days intermiſſion betwixt his two doſes, both which paſſed throughly. What wine was drunk in his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips company at <hi>Scarb.</hi> or in his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn by <hi>York,</hi> where he ſtayed two days, is impertinent either for Dr. <hi>T.</hi> or me to mention; But ſure I am, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the water nor the wine did him any great harm, ſo as to have any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence into his death. Nor had be
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:106770:58"/>any <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undice</hi> but a <hi>Cachexy,</hi> which he brought with him, neither does D. <hi>Taylor</hi> (whom he mentions) blame the water in the leaſt, againſt whoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aſion his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> undertook that long journey, and after ten or twelve days died of ſickneſs.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derman of <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi>
               </note>His ſecond inſtance is of an <hi>Alder man</hi> of <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> (p. 40) <hi>yet he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſes the Jaundice did not manifeſt it ſelf other by urine or the colour of his body, which gave him cauſe</hi> (he ſays) <hi>to ſuſpect that the water had petrified the Gall.</hi>— But I pray how came he to know it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as the <hi>Jaundice,</hi> ſince it appeared not i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the colour of the body nor the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine? If <hi>Galen</hi>'s authority be of any value or credit with him, he will tell him by his definition of <hi>Icterus,</hi> that it is an inſeparable difference whereby that d ſeaſe muſt be known, that the choler is diffuſed through the whole body in the skin. <hi>Icterus eſt effuſio hilis in cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em.</hi> So <hi>Aetius; Eſt effuſio bilioſi humoris circum corpus, ob ſecernentis cum Facultatis debilitatem.</hi> And to theſe agree all the Princes in Phyſick, as <hi>Aretaeus, Paulus, Celſus, Actuarius,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:106770:59" rendition="simple:additions"/>as the Learned may ſee in their. Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings. Yea and all our <hi>modern Writer</hi> too make it a <hi>neceſſary Adjunct,</hi> without which no man can call it a <hi>Jaundice,</hi> if it appear not in the skin. Yea if he will conſider <hi>Hippocrates</hi> or <hi>Helmon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> either,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>which are his two great Lights,</hi> (as he tells us) they will let him ſee the <hi>Jaundice</hi> is not to be judged with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it do appear in the skin. <hi>Helmo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> has indeed a large diſpute (<hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>de Hum. decept.</hi>) from whence the effu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the choler proceeds, but yet all along he denominates the <hi>Jaundice</hi> from its appearance in a yellow co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour through the whole body in the skin. And therefore I wonder our Author did not conſult better for his own Reputation in deſcribing this Diſeaſe like an <hi>Artiſt,</hi> eſpecially en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging in ſuch a deſign as this, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he could not think to eſcape unſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, either by my ſelf or ſome other. — <hi>Which gave me cauſe to ſuſpect</hi> (ſays he) <hi>that the water had petrified the gall.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>T.</hi> his new way of demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration.</note> — I muſt confeſs I can find out no ground for this his <hi>ſuſpition</hi> that the gall was petrified, nor will any
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:106770:59"/>wiſe man think it a ſufficent proof. Had he told us of the ſigns of it, in all probability they muſt have been of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſame ſize with thoſe of the <hi>Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ce.</hi> The <hi>Jaundice</hi> he fancied, and that is all the ſign we have of it, but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ece it appeared not, <hi>it gave him ground of ſuſpition,</hi> &amp;c. I will leave it to any man of reaſon to judge of, and eſpecially to thoſe of our faculty.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Alderman</hi> I well remember <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ayed at <hi>Scarb.</hi> about ſixteen days, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he water paſſed well with him, yet in that ſpace his <hi>gall is ſuſpected to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>trified.</hi>— Why! this is as ſpeedy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> petrification as that which was made to himſelf in his kidneys, and far quicker then that which is made by the <hi>Dropping-well,</hi> and its to be ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pected to gratifie him further in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ealouſie, 'twill become as ſpeedy as that of the Spring at <hi>Clarmont,</hi> and ſo by that time a draught of this water get down, it will turn into a ſtone in the ſtomach. But I wonder all this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hile that he does not name the <hi>Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,</hi> being his Neighbor and Patient, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd ſo have gained it under his hand,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:106770:60"/>which doubtleſs would have added greater force and authority to his at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation.</p>
            <p>But to give a true account of this caſe, I ſhall relate what I have from the Alderman himſelf though he is not willing to be named. <hi>He writes to me, that he was adv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſed by Dr.</hi> Tonſtal <hi>to go to</hi> Scarb. <hi>telling him it was good for his goutiſh diſtemper, with which he had been grievouſly afflicted, the waters ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rating very well during his ſtay. About a month after his return home, he was afflicted with an indigeſtion and purging which confined him to his chamber his ſtools being of a white colour; this Dr.</hi> T. <hi>ſaid was a ſymptome of the Jaundice, and another Phyſician preſcribed him ſome Chalybeate drinks which did him good, to which Dr.</hi> T. <hi>added ſome drops which he called the Eſſence of Steel, and blamed the petrifying waters of</hi> Scarb. <hi>for it, though h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> worthy Alderman ſays it was but his bare aſſertion, neither was he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that his infirmity did deſerve that denomination, having never had any the leaſt ſymptome of that diſeaſe, nor ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he ſay that the water was the cauſe of
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:106770:60" rendition="simple:additions"/>that Malady.</hi> — But I pray what ground is here for him to ſay the Gall was petrified, or that it was Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, or that the Water drunk a moneth before was in fault. It ſeems rather to have been a <hi>Flux</hi> ariſing from the debility and indigeſtion of the ſtomach, then any thing elſe, and 'tis well he cured, though he did not know wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the Merchants wife.</note>His third inſtance to prove the Spaw to breed the <hi>Jaundis</hi> is of like force and Authority with thoſe precedent: It is of a <hi>Merchants wife</hi> with childe, who after ſome few dayes drinking of this water at <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> and within <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                  <desc> _____ </desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>dayes after ſhe gate home was taken with a paine in her Right ſide</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 41) <hi>Phlebotomy was thrice ordered, then an Antimonial v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mit, yet</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>ſo obdurated was the Gall by the Petrifying property of</hi> Scarb. Water, <hi>as I ſuſpected, that none other ſigne appeared of the Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, but a return of her pain three or four times over, at length a ternary Spirit of Wine. Niter and Mercury Elixerated diſſolved the congealed Choler, and then did the diſeaſe ſhine forth in it Saffron
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:106770:61"/>Colour; after three recidivations ſhe was pluckt out of the jawes of death, beyond the hopes of all her Friends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us now examine the Caſe of this Patient as tis here laid down by <hi>Dr. T.</hi> Who becauſe he is ſo ſeverely bent from this diſeaſe to deduce an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument againſt the <hi>Spaw,</hi> I ſhall take the more liberty to conſider of it, and do not at all doubt to evince, that this Argument is as weak as thoſe that preceeded, and altogether ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs; Yea that he laboured under a grievous miſtake in reference both to his <hi>Diagnoſticks</hi> about this diſeaſe, and alſo <hi>the cure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>☞ It is a <hi>Woman with Child,</hi> and as I am certainly informed from them that know, betwixt five and fix Moneths gone. The diſeaſe is the <hi>Obduration of the Gall,</hi> the Cauſe whereof is the <hi>Petrifying Property of the Spaw;</hi> the Evidence or Proof — <hi>as he ſuſpected</hi> — To this was joyned the Jaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice, this proved by a return of pain in her Right fide three or four times over. The Remedies were Phleboto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my unto 36 ounces, as I am aſcer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:106770:61"/>by them that made Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, then an Antimonial vomit, and laſtly a Mountebank Medicine of <hi>fiery hot Spirits of Wine.</hi> Niter and Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury Elixerated does the feat, and the Saffron Colour appeares in the Skin.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duration of the Gall &amp; Jaundice.</note>I pray what proof is here of the <hi>Obduration of the Gall</hi> more then what we had in the <hi>Aldermans</hi> Caſe, (to wit) his <hi>Suſpicion,</hi> which is a new way of demonſtration, which I do wonder he would offer now the ſecond time to publike view. And what have we to prove the <hi>Jaundice?</hi> Why, nothing but his <hi>Jealouſie</hi> — a return of pain in the ſide three or four times over — I wonder where he learned, or over read of this to be a <hi>Signe</hi> of the <hi>Jandice;</hi> I dare ſay neither out of <hi>Hippocrates</hi> nor <hi>Helmount</hi> his two great Lights, no nor out of any ſolid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor.</p>
            <p>As to the means he uſed for the Cure of this Patient (to wit) to take blood in one ſo <hi>far gone with Childe, three times over, unto</hi> 36. <hi>Ounces</hi> beſides the <hi>Vomit;</hi> I'le not joyn with the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:106770:62"/>in Cenſuring him: The Caſe might be extraordinary, and then <hi>Extremis Morbis Extrema Remedia.</hi> Yet this I ſhall ſay, a Phyſician had need be upon a very ſure ground, that in ſuch a Critical caſe as this was, ſhall go in an extraordinary method, — But I muſt confeſs I cannot but laugh at his <hi>Medicine.</hi> The D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſeaſe was a violent Fever with an Acute pain in a part, and here is a violent, hot Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine, which muſt needs inflame the part more, and increaſe both the Fever and its Symptomes, and ſo bring on Relapſes. Beſides that <hi>Niter</hi> in the Spaw in ſuſpected to have <hi>petrifyed</hi> the Gall, and <hi>Congealed</hi> the Choler, and here <hi>Niter</hi> is fancyed to be the <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent.</hi> I am ſorry I am forced to point at theſe things, but I cannot avoid it, ſince they lye in my wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. — But re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally it is ſuch a H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dgpotch of Art, as I never met with before.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr. T.</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a groſs miſtake.</note>I am afraid my Friend will ſuffer more from his Brethren in the Faculty about this Diſeaſe, and its Signe, Symptomes and C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re exp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d then he did by the Women abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo <hi>often
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:106770:62"/>bleeding</hi> and <hi>vomiting</hi> this Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. The truth is, I had good grounds of Jealouſie by his Deſcription of the Caſe, that he was miſtaken in the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and therefore I writ to a Friend at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> that had oppertunities of Obſervation, enquiring if there were not joyned to the reſt of Symptomes mentioned by him, a <hi>bilious Vomiting</hi> and a <hi>Singultus:</hi> The return I had was that they were both joyned. This did aſcertin me that the diſeaſe was an <hi>Inflamation of the Liver,</hi> which had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiled him all the while; and no marvel ſhee relapſed ſo often ſince the Remedies were ſo hot. Had he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulted <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> he would have cou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celled him to another Method, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cooling and opening Medicine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. So <hi>Galen, Paulus, Celſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But its may be he will ſay, he does not approve of the old Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hod, but uſes <hi>hot things in Fevers.</hi>—It ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares ſo indeed; In the mean time that Patient is to be pittied that muſt be ſo treated. I have had occaſion to ſpeak to this point in my Anſwer to <hi>Hydrol. Chim.</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 139.) and therefore
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:106770:63"/>Il'e ſay no more now, ſince there is little danger of any young Students to become Proſelytes to our Author, that ſhall obſerve either his diſcription of Diſeaſes, or the Succeſs of his Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicines.</p>
            <p>But the Truth of the ſtory is this. It was taken at the firſt for a <hi>Pluriſie,</hi> and ſo was managed for twenty dayes, till the method proving altogether in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>effectual, Other Phyſicians were cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into Conſultation, who modeſtly confeſs they looked upon the diſeaſe as deſperate, little Room being left for Action; and do threfore blame <hi>Dr. T.</hi> for chalenging to himſelf the honour of this Cure, which was due to God alone, who beyond all hopes, and in defect of due meanes, does often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times grant a <hi>Signal Recovery.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is there any the leaſt ground to think that either the Gall was obdurated; or the Choler congea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led; but even the diffuſion of the Choler into the Skin does ſtill more plainly evince, that it was no other then the <hi>Phlegmon</hi> or <hi>Inflammation of the Liver,</hi> which happening in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:106770:63"/>or latter end of the Fever af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded a good Judication, and that the Fever would ſoon terminate.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe it ſhall appear that I offer nothing of my own private opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in this particular; I will produce the Teſtimony of ſome of our <hi>P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal</hi> W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iters in P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſick, to prove that Symptomes here reckoned up as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concurring in this Patient, do moſt cer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ainly denote the <hi>Inflamation of the Liver,</hi> and no other diſeaſe. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f a Phyſician miſtake the diſeaſe, he muſt undoubtedly fail of the Cure, or ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard the Patient with frequent Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſes. And in this I refer to the Judgment of all the Learned Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of our Faculty.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</note>
               <hi>Aretaeus</hi> (<hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>de re med. Cap. a Morbo Regio</hi>) Expreſſes it thus. <hi>St [M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rbus Regius] cumfebre &amp; bilioſis ejectionibus fiat, &amp; gravitas ſit circa dextrum praecordium, inflammatio fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens judicatur ipſius Hepatis, ob quam bileſcens Sanguis per totum Corpus fertur.</hi> To which Ile add that of <hi>Cornelius Cel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> (lib. 2. de re med. cap. 7)) <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent Singultus &amp; praeter conſuetudinem
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:106770:64"/>continuus, jecur inflammatum eſſe ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cat;</hi> and a little after,—<hi>Si Hepar inflammatum eſt, dolor in communiomni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus adeſt in dextro Hypochondrio, tranſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens ſurſum ad Claviculam</hi> (this I gueſs made our Author think it to be a Pleurifie.) <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orſum ad ſpurias uſque Coſtas, ebris acuta, tuſſes ſiccae, ſitis, cibi inappetentia, ſpirandi difficultas, &amp; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vus Suppreſſa eſt.</hi> And <hi>Actius</hi> recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning up the ſignes of the Inflammation of the Liver, mentions theſe—<hi>Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris acuta inaequalis, ſpirandi difficultas, tuſſiculae parvae ut plurimum ſiccae, vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiones bilioſae, Coſtae ut plurimum condoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant, Corporis Color Subvertitur, &amp; in Arquati ſpeciem permutatur, ſingult<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s quoque conſequuntur.</hi> —From hence nothing can more plainly appear, then that this diſeaſe was in truth the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flammation of the Liver;</hi> The yellow colour of the skin being one ſigne among the reſt, coming in the cloſe of the fever, and conſequently it was not the effect of the <hi>Spaw,</hi> but of the <hi>Phlegmon</hi> of the Part,</p>
            <p>And as he miſtook in his <hi>Diagno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticks</hi> or judging of the diſeaſe, ſo I muſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:106770:64"/>in kindneſs to him and his Buſineſs for the future, (if he will accept it ſo) let him know, that he was out of his <hi>Therapeuticks</hi> or the Remedies, that <hi>ternary Spirit of Wine, Niter.</hi> &amp;c. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as improper as any thing he could have pitcht upon, which who ſo uſes in like caſe, muſt expect nothing leſs then a long diſeaſe, as this proved to be, and frequent Relapſes, to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream hazard of the Patients life. <hi>Ad calidam Hepatis intemperiem utendum <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſet perfrigerantibus, &amp; corroborantibus Viſcus moderate, &amp;c. A Vino in to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum Aegri abſtineant, ni ob aliam Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam nempe ſtomachi debilitatem utan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, &amp; tunc tenne &amp; parum aquae fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ns aquoſum ipſis detur.</hi> So ſayes <hi>Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Aegineta</hi> (<hi>de re med. c.</hi> 46. <hi>de hep. effect</hi>) Here a cooling diet is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and Wine <hi>wholy</hi> forbiden, and much more Spirit of Wine.</p>
            <p>Thus I have ſifted theſe three Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which he brings in to pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e that this water cauſed the <hi>Jaundice,</hi> or <hi>petrifyed the Gal,</hi> and have found them all very weak, and not to have been bottomed on <hi>Reaſon</hi> or <hi>Verity.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="96" facs="tcp:106770:65"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Spaw cures the Jaundice.</note>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> I were diſpoſed and it were needful to bring inſtances of Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence in this point. I could multiply <hi>Cures of the Jaundice</hi> by this water. I ſhall content my ſelf with two for brevity ſake. <hi>Sir John Legards</hi> Lady of <hi>Ganton</hi> within a few miles of <hi>Scarb.</hi> had a <hi>Jaundice</hi> that long reſiſted Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medies in a Rational Method, and was perfectly cured by the Spaw in a few dayes, being thereto recommended by another Lady, who had Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced a Cure in the ſame Diſeaſe; and this conſented to by <hi>Dr. Arnold</hi> hir Phyſician, who knew it to be a Rational advice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Mr. William Hodgſon</hi> Miniſter of <hi>Scarbrough</hi> was for the ſpace of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> yeares, ever and anon falling into the <hi>Jaundice,</hi> eſpecially Spring and Fall nay, one time it continued upon him almoſt all the year, notwithſtanding his Endeavours after a Cure: I Since he was ſetled at <hi>Scarb.</hi> which is now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout four years, he has found a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Cure by the Spaw.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing our Author is ſo extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſevere, as that he has ſo f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:106770:65"/>ſtretched to prove this water to be <hi>ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive,</hi> I judge it very pertinent here to tell a ſtory, which to him is <hi>Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum ad hominem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anno 1668. Dr. <hi>Tonſtal</hi> came to ☜ me at <hi>Scarb.</hi>
               <note place="margin">A rare cure of Dr. <hi>T's</hi> Wife.</note> pretending his only bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſineſs was to take my advice about his Wife, whoſe belly never fell after a Child that ſhe had born, not could he with all his Art take it down, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he had uſed much means about it, as he told me. <hi>If</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>you can adviſe to any method that may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it, or you think the Spaw may conduce thereto, for you underſtand it better then I who am a ſtranger to it, then I will ſend for her, elſe Ile return forthwith.</hi>—To be ſhort, after ſome queries which I made, being reſolved— I adviſed him to ſend for her not doubting of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cure; ſo he did, and within one week ſhe came by ſea from <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi> Then he brought her to me, with whom I had ſome conference while we took three or four turns upon the ſands. I adviſed her Husband to give her ſome preparatives, and ſomething <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe with the water to further the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:106770:66"/>After a few days her bodies did lace cloſe, that could not meet within three or four inches before. She continued to drink a month, and returned perfectly well, and ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues to this day, free from all ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, it being near <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hree years ſince. But we have not a <hi>ſyllable</hi> of this in his Book.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thankful.</note>Now this water that could open the <hi>Lact<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ae,</hi> and ſmall veins of the meſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, which was the means of this cure, how can it be thought to be an <hi>obſtructive</hi> water, and to breed the <hi>Jaundice?</hi> I leave it to the judgement of wiſe and impartial men, nay to himſelf to pauſe on, the Cure being ſufficiently known at <hi>Newcaſtle.</hi> Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly its an ill requital which here he makes to the <hi>Spaw</hi> for that <hi>excellent</hi> Cure, and he is extreamly diſinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious.</p>
            <p>Nothing is more ordinary then to ſee (at theſe waters) thoſe that are corpulent, taken down in their bellies more or leſs, even ſometimes a <hi>ſpan,</hi> when they are willing to follow ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, that ſome few other medicin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:106770:66"/>may be joyned to further the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which could not poſſibly be done if it were <hi>obſtructive.</hi> Nor is there a better thing in nature for taking away the reliques of all inveterate Agues,<note place="margin">It cures Agues.</note> which ſufficiently makes it out to be aperitive.</p>
            <p>It is found in dayly experience to be very beneficial againſt the <hi>Scurvy</hi> refining the Blood,<note place="margin">So the Scurvy</note> ſtrengthening the natural parts, and correcting all the ſymptomes of it, which fully evinces it to be of a <hi>deoppilative</hi> or <hi>opening</hi> vertue: Beſides the <hi>purging</hi> property which all along he acknowledges, is directly contrary to the <hi>obſtructive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An aged Gentleman Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Adams</hi> of <hi>Camelsford</hi> in <hi>York-ſhire,</hi> ſeventy three years old, well known to our Author himſelf, in vexation againſt theſe <hi>frivolous cavils</hi> of his, offers me this his teſtimony, which he accounts himſelf obliged in juſtice to give. <hi>viz.</hi> That for ſix years toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was miſerably tormented with pain in his legs, feebleneſs in his knees, frequent faintings, and a dry itch over all his skin. He had adviſed
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:106770:67"/>with ſeveral Phyſitians, who had or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him <hi>Diet-drinks, Diaphoreticks, Oyntments,</hi> &amp;c. but without any ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs at all. He came at length to <hi>Scarb.</hi> and upon drinking of that water found perfect eaſe in all theſe ſaid ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptomes. He had alſo been ſore afflicted with dizzineſs in his head, and loſs of memory; his underſtanding alſo was ſometimes ſo clouded, that he could not diſcern the quarters of Heaven, or know the <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt</hi> from the <hi>Weſt,</hi> and ſometimes was wont to fall. By the uſe of the <hi>Spaw</hi> he recovered out of all the ſaid ſymptomes, and never had any fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s ſince conſiderable; for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention whereof he has continued his annual viſits at <hi>Scarbrough</hi> theſe ſeven years, though he lives at forty miles diſtance.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dr <hi>T.</hi> is cenſured by the Women.</note>But I may not paſs it over that out Author tells us he fell under the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>quy and cenſure of the women for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſeverity to the <hi>Merchant's Wife</hi> we mentioned even now, which puts him to his vindication, (<hi>p.</hi> 42.) where he bids them <hi>take notice that it is his prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple when he ſees his duty, to purſue it to
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:106770:67"/>the hazzard of his credit,</hi> &amp;c. — I do indeed take him to be an honeſt man, and a faithful Phyſitian, and here to clear up all ſcruple, we have it now the ſecond time under his own hand; For (<hi>p.</hi> 14.) <hi>he had told his Friends, he gave no worſe counſel to them then he took himſelf, and wiſhes that all Phyſitians were bound with his girdle</hi> — <hi>and here he will hazzard his credit in the doing of his duty</hi>— What can a man ſay more to make out his integrity? though honeſty tends little to the curing of diſeaſes, but that its neceſſary a Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian endeavour after other accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliſhments, that he may underſtand aright both the nature of Diſeaſes, leſt he miſtake one for another, and alſo the matter of Phyſick that he may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply ſutable remedies: Yet it is ſo va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luable a qualification, that all perſons that are ingenious, know how preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a thing a good name is, when they ſee it ſo eminently appear, ſhould forbear to be cenſorious, eſpecially when they are not able to diſcern but that he may be in the right, other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife it is the greateſt diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:106770:68"/>that a Phyſitian can fall under.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">He taxes his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</note>Had our Author deſiſted here he had been much more innocent, but having juſtified himſelf he condemns his Brethren of the Faculty. <hi>And though</hi> (ſays he) <hi>I be ſingular in this point from the moſt of my Brethren, whoſe wiſdom it is to ſecure themſelves from an evil report, by doing nothing in a doubtful caſe, yet I have not ſo learned Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>How ſutes this with Reaſon or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, when he is blaming the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men for their raſh cenſuring of him, that with the ſame breath he ſhould cenſure others? while he tells us he is ſingular in this point from the moſt of his Brethren, does it not ſavour too much like that of the Phariſee, I am not like this Publican? what mans wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom can ſuffice to ſecure himſelf from an evil report, when ſome mens pens or tongues are ſo laviſh as we finde them? doubtleſs he that has learned <hi>Chriſt</hi> aright, will take care to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it in love and charity towards others, and Charity judges the beſt, and cenſures no man.</p>
            <pb n="103" facs="tcp:106770:68"/>
            <p>Again in ſuch doubtfull Caſes its ever the ſafeſt for a Phyſician to call in for the Advice and help of his Brethren, and not to hazard the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious life of any perſon in making dubious and private Experiments. And what hopes can a Patient have from a conſultation of Phyſicians, when they are not in Charity one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</p>
            <p>In this his ſevere Cenſure, I would hope he does not fix it upon his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren at a diſtance, whoſe practiſe he knowes not: And as for thoſe that are neer about him, I know ſeveral of them ſo well, that I muſt needs ſay, I think there is not any cauſe, why they ſhould be excluded from having an equal Magnanimity with himſelf in this point.</p>
            <p>But there is one thing I may not overlook (<hi>p.</hi> 38.) he tels us <hi>he was preſent at Phyſick-Lecture in London, where the Profeſſour diſcourſing of the Jaundice, brought forth three or four Stones that had been bred in the Gall, which he had cauſed a Gentltwoman to void (by ſtool) with a ſharp Doſe of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:106770:69"/>Phiſick.</hi> — I am afraid our A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor was miſtaken in the Profeſſors D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſcourſe for what paſſage is there from the Gall to the Guts to convey Stones, and how could he think by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Doſe of Phiſick to excite Nature to expel them out of the Gall? I ſuſpect the <hi>Ductus Cholid chu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> will not afford ſufficient paſſage for Stones, (which ſometimes I have ſeen to be very large, and in the form of a race of Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger) no more then the ſmall veines of the Meſentery will admit of Sand or Gravel to paſs into the Kidneys, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the matter of ſtones there.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the Gowt.</note>(P. 43. <hi>He accuſes it to be ill for the Gowt, and cites his own Cafe, that it made him go limping a Fortnight after.</hi> — But I ſuſpect he takes <hi>Non Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſam pro Cauſa,</hi> but in this as in every thing elſe, he makes himſelf both Plaintiffe, and Witneſs, and Judge. This is ſo much contrary to the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of it as Water, which is a good Preſervative againſt the Gowt, and as ſuch a water, that is impregnated with thoſe Mineral Principles in which we are agreed, that it deſerves no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:106770:69"/>Reply. — Beſides the Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence my ſelf, who have had ſome gentle fits of the Gowt, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral others who have ever found it a good Preven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tive, even when there has been ſome inclination to it by cooling the Maſs of Blood, and cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting and purging the Acrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious Hamours; only I ever joyn ſome other thing to further the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The Spaw needs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paratives.</note>(P. 44.) <hi>He ſayes no Spaw in the World has leſs need of Preparatives, and more need of Purges then this, and that he never obſerved that any at the firſt morning Draught wanted a ſpeedy paſſage by the back doore.</hi>—Herein I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare his Obſervation to come ſhort, for though it ordinarily it failes not to paſs through at the firſt, yet ſome Conſtitutions there are eſpecially eſpecially ſuch as are Melancholick, and others whoſe Bodies ore wont to be Conſtipated, eſpecially women in whom it will ſcarce find paſſage in a day or two, in ſuch there is an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Neceſſity of Preparatives. The water is indeed nimble and ſometimes
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:106770:70"/>has wrought ten dayes together, while yet it has but made a furrow through the Outs, and has left all the Excre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentitious humours behind it, the party finding therein no benefit at all, when with a Cathartick I uſed, he voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Cherry-ſtones, whereas for thoſe ten dayes he had eaten no Cherries. Beſides, although we could be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that it would paſs freely, yet as for thoſe that come with any Chronical Diſeaſe of which they expect to finde a Cure, there is a neceſſity both to prepare the body, and alſo to furniſh the Patient with other Concomitant Medicincs to be uſed with the waters, ſutable to the Malady and the Patients Conſtitution, otherwiſe notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dayly working of the water, they may return as they came.</p>
            <p>Nor is it poſſible for me to lay down Rules to ſute every Caſe, though I ſhould run out into a Volume; thoſe depend upon daily Obſervation, and frequent converſe with the Patient, on which account I have been uſually there every Summer theſe twenty years and upwards, and So may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bably
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:106770:70"/>continue at the due ſeaſon while God ſpares me life and Health. In the mean time I muſt take leave to refer the kind Reader to what I have ſaid more at large upon this point of direction in the uſe of the Spaw in my Book called <hi>Scarbrough Spaw, Edit.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtency of his Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſertions.</note>Now the eminent purging proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty which here he confeſſes to be in the Water, doth make it much more ſafe in thoſe very caſes wherein he has charged it to be faulty, then other waters of this kind, which paſs not by ſiege, bu only <hi>work by Vrine,</hi> (as they expreſs it) which Wine, Whey, or any other kind of liquor will do.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, in regard of the <hi>Stone;</hi> Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by are the groſs and ſlimy Humours that lie on this ſide the Kidneys in a good meaſure caſt out by the Bowels, and the Patient is ſecured from an <hi>Iſchuria</hi> or total ſtopping of Urine, which has too frequently happened at other waters that over paſs by Urine; The ſlimy water being carried by the ſole Diuretick property of thoſe wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters upon the narrow paſſages of
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:106770:71"/>Urine, and thereupon has enſued a to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal ſtopping, to the ſpeedy ruine of the Patient, whereas (God be praiſed) ſuch a eaſe never happened at <hi>Scarlrough.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, hereby not only the groſs Excrementitious Humours, but alſo the <hi>Stone-filings</hi> (if I ſhould grant any ſuch thing to be in the Water) muſt be carryed down the broad way by the Bowels, and ſo cannot poſſibly be thrown upon the narrow paſſages, to become the Material cauſe of a ſtone in the Body.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, this <hi>purging</hi> property does quite Overtthrow what before he had aſſerted concerning the waters <hi>Obſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> property, for 'tis impoſſible that the ſame thing ſhould be ſo eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Purgative</hi> and alſo <hi>Obſtructive</hi> to cauſe the Jaundice.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, that Property which he charges on it, as that it cauſes the <hi>Gowt,</hi> cannot poſſibly conſiſt with this that here he aſſerts concerning the <hi>ſpeedy Purging,</hi> eſpecially while we conſider what he acknowledged in <hi>p.</hi> 25. to wit, that it purges well a moneth together, and what further he will tell us <hi>p.</hi> 62.
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:106770:71" rendition="simple:additions"/>that it may endanger a <hi>Diſcentery;</hi> For <hi>purging</hi> is owned by all, and preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed as a ſpecial Remedy againſt the <hi>Gowt,</hi> either to prevent or to Cure it.</p>
            <p>And therefore ſeeing he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to fix ſo <hi>ſevere</hi> a Charge upon the Spaw, I wonder he did not take care ſo to draw it up, as that one piece might not enterfer with and confute another.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of Vitiral and Iron.</note>(Pag. 45. He would pretend to deny <hi>Vitriol</hi> and <hi>Iron</hi> to be in the Spaw; ſo did Mr. <hi>S.</hi> and at length recanted, and ſo will he perhaps in time. But both theſe I have ſufficient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proved in my Book of <hi>Scar, Spaw,</hi> and have enlarged upon them both in my Anſwer to <hi>Hydrol. Chim.</hi> and have further made it out from the Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of good Authors that have trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on ſuch Subjects, and more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly of the Chimical Writers, that the <hi>Acidity, Inky ſmell,</hi> and <hi>black T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture from Gall</hi> are certain and unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable Arguments to prove <hi>Vitriol.</hi> I will not trouble the Reader with a repetion of what there I have ſaid, but do refer him to my Book. Nay fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:106770:72"/>within theſe two years our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor himſelf was abundantly convin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced of the preſence of them both.</p>
            <p>I deny not but <hi>Nitre</hi> may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute ſome Acidity to Water, (<hi>as he ſayes p.</hi> 59) though I exclude the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Nitre</hi> as extraneous to our Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject.—As for his experiment which he propounds to paralel the ſmell of <hi>Scar. Spaw,</hi> concerning which (he ſayes) <hi>he will forfeit his Noſe, if it do not ſtink worſe then the Alome-pans at Whithy;</hi> I wonder to find him ſo zealous in this Point, to fix a ſtinking ſmell upon that water, when there are ſo many thouſands to confute him, I am perſwaded not a Countey in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> but it affords many that are able to contradict him in this. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; though hence it may appear he has loſt his Smell, yet I ſhould be hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily ſory, that for ſo ſmall a miſtake my friend ſhould forfeit his Noſe.</p>
            <p>The very truth is, it has a perfect <hi>Vitrioline</hi> ſmell, which no man will deny, ſave thoſe that proſecute a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigne of contradiction, which being once engaged in, they are not willing
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:106770:72"/>to give over, notwithwanding all grounds of Conviction that can be imagined, and with which moſt wiſe and Learned men of our Nation have been fully ſatisfied.</p>
            <p>And whereas <hi>he tells</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 54.) <hi>of a Water at Hunwick, nere which Iron-Stone is digged; that receives a Tincture with Gall, as highly as Soar. Spaw,</hi> (though its mention makes nothing to his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.) Why may not that have the Vitriol of Iron in it, eſpecially ſeeing the Iron ſtone is ſo nigh. However <hi>&amp; quae non proſunt ſingular juncta juvant.</hi> Since all theſe Properties (to wit) its <hi>Acidity, Vitrioline ſmell,</hi> and <hi>Tinging Blackwith</hi> Gall are all met together, it makes an undeniable Argument that here is <hi>Vitriol.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Dr. <hi>T.</hi> has changed his minde.</note>I do ſeriouſly profeſs, that when in <hi>Anno</hi> 1668. <hi>Dr. T.</hi> came firſt to <hi>Scarb.</hi> he owned both the <hi>Votriol</hi> and the <hi>Iron</hi> beſide the reſt, having conviction from the reaſons which I gave him, and fell into admiration to ſee ſo many excellent Minerals meet in that place, which gave me occaſion to mention it in my Anſwer to <hi>Hydrol. Ghim.</hi> (p. 107.)
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:106770:73"/>with more ſincere reſpect to him then now he deſerves, ſince he has ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſelefly changed his minde. But he that on ſuch ſlender grounds can af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm at this rate, as we have found in this his Book, may as eaſily deny what he will. That which was <hi>Vitriol</hi> laſt year is this year become <hi>Nitre.</hi>— Well! I have proved <hi>Vitriol</hi> to be in it by ſuch Arguments as Learned men have contented themſelves withal in the like Caſes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and by an Induction of the inſeparable properties of <hi>Vitriol,</hi> which I diſcern in the water, and that or large in former Books, yet becauſe I would do ſomewhat more for this my Friends Conviction, I ſhall <hi>ex <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundanti</hi> caſt him in one Author more; and he a <hi>Chymiſt</hi> too; it is <hi>Petrus Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haennes Faber</hi> in his <hi>Hydrog. Spagy.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Fabers</hi> Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony.</note> lib. 1. cap. 9. p. 39.) where treating of Springs that have imbibed <hi>Sulpher, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Nigreſcit</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>borum Fontium liquor, ſi gallae in pulverem re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dastae in ipſum fontis liquorem proijcian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, quol vitriolum verum ac certum teſtatur,</hi> to wit, The waters of theſe Fountaines turn black if the powder
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:106770:73" rendition="simple:additions"/>of Galls be put into it, and that is as true and undoubted Teſtimony that there is <hi>Vitriol</hi> in it.</p>
            <p>So again (<hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c</hi> 11 <hi>p.</hi> 164. The ſame Author telling of two Springs at <hi>Vi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>le Comt,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>untey of <hi>Averne</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> the one called <hi>La Fountain du Cornet,</hi> the other <hi>La Fountain du Rocker,</hi> he ſayes, they are both of one Notur, and have a <hi>Vitriol</hi> in them, which he proves by two Arguments that we have been mentioning, <hi>(vid.)</hi> their <hi>Taſte,</hi> and their <hi>black Tinctur</hi> with G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l.—<hi>Habent ſecum vitriolum diſſolutum, ut ex guſtu ipſam equm in atramentum: quae fique vera ſunt &amp; legitima admix<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Vitrioli,</hi> which are ſayes he, the true and legitimate ſignes of <hi>Vitriol.</hi> Beſides the admirable vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which he reports to be in thoſe Springs, for opening the Obſtuctions of the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ver, Spleen and Meſſentery, and for the purging of viſcous hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, (eminently true in this of ours of <hi>Scarb.</hi>) at the length be adds — <hi>Nullus fere morbus dari po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt, quin hiſce aquis curari poſſit</hi> —You can ſcarce name any diſeaſe
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:106770:74" rendition="simple:additions"/>(ſayes he) which may not he cured with theſe waters.</p>
            <p>Now why we ſhould forfeit our reaſon, and Spurn at the ſolid Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Learned Writers in all Ages and parts of the World, who have thus contented themſelves to ſpeak concerning this thing, and <hi>ſubmittere faſces</hi> to the Magiſterial Dictates and Reſolutions of ſome ſelf-conceited O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions, I ſee no ground for it. And though I cannot ſay with <hi>Faber</hi> that this <hi>Spaw</hi> cures all diſeaſes, Yet I am certain it is far more innocent then his Springs, which he confeſſes do provoke vomit, and ſometimes purg unto blood; on which account he mixes ordinary Spring water with them to correct the Acrimony of the <hi>Vitriol.</hi> And this I ſhall further ſay, that no Spring in <hi>Europe</hi> hitherto diſcovered, may be further improved for the Cure of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious diſeaſes then this, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by the particulars I have mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in my Book on the <hi>Spaw,</hi> as alſo theſe I have now expreſſed on this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acaſion: Nor I think can the wit of man invent a better Compoſition, then
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:106770:74"/>by Divine Providence is here adapted for the good of mankind.</p>
            <p>(Page 54.) <hi>He ſays no Vitriol but that which is Ferrugineum will take a tincture from Gall.</hi>— I would fain know then how it comes to paſs that <hi>white Vitriol</hi> will make Ink, is this <hi>ferrugine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> or made out of Iron? ſurely no, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t I am ſure it will make Ink. Will he fall out with the Author of <hi>Hydrol. Chymica,</hi> who (<hi>p.</hi> 5.) makes <hi>Vitriol of Iron,</hi> and <hi>white Vitriol</hi> really to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer? — However he makes this an argument to exclude both <hi>Vitriol</hi> and <hi>Iron</hi> out of the number of the Mineral Principles, owning nothing but <hi>Nitre</hi> and the <hi>Glebe of Alome,</hi> both which I have ſufficiently proved in my former Books, to the full ſatisfaction (I hope) of every impartial Reader.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He ſays</hi> (p. 49.) <hi>that he ſaw a piece of Alome-ſtone which the Chymical Apothe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary took out of the Earth near the Spaw, which with Gall gave a black tincture to Spring-water.</hi>— I am afraid the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecary was too nimble for the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, and took that Stone out of the <hi>Vitrioline</hi> Bed, which I mention (<hi>p.</hi> 44.)
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:106770:75"/>of my Anſwer, which indeed will Tincture becauſe it is impregnated with <hi>Vitriol</hi> (as alſo with the Earth in that Bed, from whence he may as well infer, that all ſorts of Earth will with Gall give a Tincture to Water) whereas the many hundred loads of Alome-Stone, or Earth, that is there beſides will give no tincture, except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in one other place within a few yards of the Spaw<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> where I found ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bed of <hi>Vitriol</hi> laſt year. But of this I have ſaid enough in that Book.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>He contents himſelf with proving Kna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>resb. Spaw to be Vitrioline</hi> (p. 57.) <hi>by the yellow colour wherewith the Baſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n and Spout of that Spring are tinctured, which he calls</hi> Crocus Martis; <hi>and the like</hi> (he ſayes) <hi>may be obſerved in every Runner near the head of any Vitrioline or Chaly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beate Spring.</hi>— I now appeal to his own eyes, whether it be not ſo at <hi>Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brough?</hi> — But whether this be a good Argument to prove <hi>Vitriol</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> matters not much, Learned Writers mentioning no ſuch ſign of <hi>Vitriol</hi> but rather that it denotes <hi>Iron.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever if it be at all convincing, as to
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:106770:75"/>him it is, then <hi>à fortiori</hi> it makes emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently for <hi>Scarbrough,</hi> becauſe it has a deeper dye than tha at <hi>Knaresbr.</hi> having alſo the ſubſtance of that which he calls <hi>Crocus Martas,</hi> not to be found in the other.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Of the Pinfold.</note>But while he is debating upon theſe two Minerals of <hi>Vitriol</hi> and <hi>Iron,</hi> and the Tincture which the Water takes with Gall, he makes himſelf merry with me, <hi>while he fancies to have got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten me into a Pinfold,</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 54.) Why may not I be merry too ſince I have found the way out? I wonder where my good Brother learned the Art of making a <hi>Pinfold.</hi> I have read of two famous <hi>Pinfolds,</hi> one at <hi>Wakefield,</hi> where ſometimes dwelt a very ſtout and ſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy Pinder, of whom we have an anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent merry ſong in <hi>York ſhire.</hi> Another was made at <hi>Gotam,</hi> where the wiſe men of that Town did put themſelves to a great charge and trouble to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound the Cuckow,<note place="margin">The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagoniſt Mr. <hi>S.</hi> lives at <hi>Wakefield.</hi>
               </note> which quickly overtopt the <hi>Pinfold,</hi> and left the Builders in a maze to bewail their folly. From which of theſe he derives his Craft, I know no. But the former
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:106770:76"/>could not hold me, I am very well delivered with my bones whole. And the latter I doubt not to creep through or overtop, unleſs it be made with more Art then yet I can diſcover in the framing.</p>
            <p>(Page 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.) He is diſcourſing about the <hi>Earth,</hi> which I mention <hi>p.</hi> 14. that falling from the Cliff near the <hi>Spaw,</hi> is converted into an <hi>Iron-ſtone,</hi> and is fuſible in the fire. — This he is not pleaſed withal, but declares his opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of it, which I muſt confeſs I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not make good ſenſe, unleſs the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der help me, <hi>To me</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>it doth appear to be a rediſh Earth diſſolved with the N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>troaluminous Salt, and petrified in the Sun and Air to a hard lump.</hi> — Here is <hi>Earth diſſolved with Salt,</hi> and <hi>petrified!</hi> What ſhall I ſay? <hi>Si non vult intelligi debet negligi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I return.<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>T.</hi> is magiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial.</note>
               <hi>P.</hi> 49. he determines Magiſterially. — <hi>I ſay 'tis only the Alome-ſtone that gives the Tincture— Let Experience prove it. Take Alome-Stone unburnt, powder it, add Spring-water ſharpened with Spirit of Nitre, that it may diſſolve it— put Gall to it, and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:106770:76"/>it gives you the ſame Tincture.</hi>— Alas! This with much more that I have met with in this piece is borrowed from my <hi>Antagoniſt.</hi> to whom I gave Anſwer fully and at large, nor does he wield the Club much better, or has any new gard. I ſay again what have we to do here with the <hi>Spirit of Nitre</hi> to diſſolve the <hi>Alom-ſtone?</hi> Let him keep to his Sample, in <hi>Scar. Spaw,</hi> there is no <hi>Sprit of Nitre,</hi> nor any <hi>Fire</hi> to Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract it. Indeed <hi>Nitre</hi> there is, and to that let him hold cloſe: But I aſſure him that neither the <hi>Nitre</hi> that Sweats out of the earth neer the well, not yet our ordinary <hi>Nitre of the Shops</hi> d ſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in water, to which let be joyned <hi>Alome-ſtone</hi> Crude or Calcined (though we have nothing to do with latter here) or if he pleaſes joyn <hi>perfect Alome,</hi> made either with Kelp and Urine, or without them; I ſay theſe mixe together ſhall never qualify Water, to take a a black <hi>Tinctur</hi> from Gall it <hi>Vitrial</hi> be away. And this that I ſay any man ſhall find to be true, if he put it to Experiment. So that upon the whole matter, my firſt <hi>Theſis</hi> ſtrands firm, and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:106770:77"/>unſhaken, that it is the <hi>Vitriol</hi> alone, that gives the black Tincture with Gall, and conſequently that <hi>Scarb. Spaw</hi> is a <hi>Vitrioline</hi> Spring.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> But now comes our Author with his battering Ramme, with which he not only ſhakes the building, but raſes even the Foundation of <hi>Scar. Spaw,</hi> while yet he pretends to be its <hi>great Friend.</hi> (<hi>p.</hi> 45. <hi>If</hi> (ſays he) <hi>the Eſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rit of Vitriol be ioyned with the Volati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Spirit of Nitre in the Water, how does it differ from Aqua Fortis, which is a deadly Corroſive? And if it be ſaid theſe are not all, there is Alome and Salt alſo; This makes it worſe, even an</hi> Aqua Regia, <hi>which will corrod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Gold, and conſequently it muſt be poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> I anſwer; Methink he deales with the <hi>Spaw</hi> as <hi>Joab</hi> did with <hi>Abner,</hi> of whom its ſad, 2 Sam. 3.27. <hi>That he took him a ſide to ſpeak with him p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably, or as a Friend, and then he ſmote him into the fifth Ril.</hi> Is this a token of his Friendſhip to make it poyſonous? I am glad his W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fe lives to confute him. If it will but diſſolve a ſtone in
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:106770:77"/>the body, no matter whether it will diſſolve Gold or no. I ſay again what have we to do with the <hi>Spirits of Vitri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ol and Nitre,</hi> and what aims he to prove by his <hi>Firſt. Second,</hi> and <hi>Thirdly?</hi> What though <hi>Vitriol</hi> and <hi>Nitre diſtilled</hi> together raiſe a <hi>Corroſive</hi> Spirit? So will Rye-bread Diſtilled afford an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tream <hi>Corroſive</hi> Spirit that will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve Metal, if he will truſt Maſter <hi>Boyle</hi> —</p>
            <p>Such alteration does fire make in it, and what though, ſince the World knowes its wholeſome, we are not afraid of thoſe <hi>Spirits</hi> in the wate<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, I am certain they are but Phantaſmes, and ſignifie nothing.</p>
            <p>Here we find a Water which many thouſand of perſons of all ages and both Sexes have liberally drunk of for theſe fourty years, with excellent ſucceſs in the Cure of great diſeaſes, when they were well adviſed, and followed counſel) working without Griping or the leaſt C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſion, and purging without Superpurgation. In a word many hundreds there are who will give this or a further Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:106770:78"/>when occaſion ſhall be offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and tell the World that all his Reaſoning to the contrary is but frivolous.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Another Charge</note>And this Leads me to the laſt charge, which is the <hi>Sting in the Tail,</hi> and if it be proved makes it an unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donable fault, to wit, that <hi>the duplicated Salt may be in danger to corrode the Bowles, and cauſe a dyſentery.</hi>—I am afraid ſome would have it ſe. But tis enough that he has ſaid it, for as he has not ſolidly proved any thing a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, ſo he does not attempt to do it here, And as he does not, So neither can I. No water in the world is more ſafe then this in that very point. The Conjunction of <hi>Alome</hi> and <hi>Iron,</hi> two <hi>Aſtringents,</hi> with the other that are <hi>Attenuating</hi> and <hi>Penetrative,</hi> as I have proved to conduce to the better for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifying of the Liver, and other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural parts, So they contribute to the ſafegard of the Belly from <hi>Fluxes.</hi> which never happen to them that do drink regularly at the Fountain. Nay I have often known <hi>inveterate dyſente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> and other <hi>Fluxes</hi> cured by it.</p>
            <pb n="123" facs="tcp:106770:78" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">A rate cure in a Flux.</note>
               <hi>Silveſter Sympſon of Driffield Yorksh.</hi> had a bloody Flux eight years, ſo as he all that Space was forced to riſe to ſtool every night three or four times; It had reſiſted all other means he had attempted. He went to <hi>Scarb.</hi> and was cured perfectly in two or three dayes with the water alone.</p>
            <p>This I have examined what may ſeem to be material in his Book, only omitting ſome impertinencies, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry Expreſſions as not worthy to be reflected on. I am of opinion that an angry fit is very wholſom for ſome Conſtitutions, though it may make a man uneaſie to his Company for the preſent, and thoſe that come within his reach: Yet when the Ebullition of Choller is over, it leaves a man in a far more Sedtae temper of mind for a good while after, then before he was wont to be, and more gay and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placent in his humour to others. If my Friend having given his <hi>Spleen</hi> this vent, be the better for it in his <hi>Cranium,</hi> I ſhould be very glad; as indeed I am informed, he did ſeem to be much pleaſed with what he had
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:106770:79"/>done in this P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ece,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> XII</note> and became more frolick then formerly.</p>
            <p>(<hi>P.</hi> 45.) It appears by the laſt <hi>Paragraph</hi> of his Book that he had ſome perſwaſion that herein he has perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome rare piece of Art,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Dr. T.</hi> is conceited of ſo e merit in his Piece</note> wherein he expects to be applauded by me, for he cites a place out of my Anſwer to Mr. <hi>S. p.</hi> 2, 8) where my words are, <hi>that if Mr. S. hath any thing to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ke out in point of Art, I would never go about to Eclipſe his Honour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation in it, but would thank him</hi> — And this our Author adds, that <hi>as I am a man of my word, He expects thus much from me.</hi> I anſwer, I cannot but approve a piece of Art, where ever I find it, and as I ſhall perform my word to <hi>Mr. S.</hi> who is alone concerned in that promiſe, ſo in Juſtice I ſhall not deny it to him when I ſee it. B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t as for this P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ece I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee not the leaſt point of Art in it, from the beginning to the end. I refer it to the Learned and impartial Reader to judge betwixt u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Nay I prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſerio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſly were I conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous that theſe his Pretended diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries were true, and that there were
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:106770:79"/>any real ground for this his Carping at this water, (though there be noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng of Art in the making of them out) <hi>I</hi> would let him ride<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion with his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and thank him to boot. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſured of his totall miſtake, and having ſo made it out. I muſt needs let him know, that all his Perſwaſion of Merit in this P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ece is but a <hi>Melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Fancy,</hi> and is ſo far from deſerving applauſe, that ſomewhiles <hi>I</hi> have thought it needed not, nor deſerved an Anſwere, ſince there are many hundreds that do but laugh when they read it, being able to confute it from their own O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſervation; and among them ſome of his own Neighbours and Patients, who have expreſſed their admiration, what frame he was in when he writ this Book.</p>
            <p>Now becauſe there are ſome that are not able to judge of the force of Arguments, <hi>I</hi> ſhall for their ſakes add thus much. That as I deſire in all things to be found faithful as becomes me, either as a <hi>Phyſician</hi> or a <hi>Chriſtian;</hi> ſo in this diſpute <hi>I</hi> aim not ſo much at <hi>Victory</hi> as <hi>Truth,</hi> which in Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:106770:80"/>and Reputation, (eſpecially be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called to it ſo often by name) <hi>I</hi> think my ſelf obliged to defend, in the maintenance of the Fame of this moſt excellent Spring, againſt the ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs cavils of this Gentleman. Nor do <hi>I</hi> think that there is a more innocent Water of this kind in the World, at this day diſcovered, in the very par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars he has charged in withall, in all which caſes <hi>I</hi> declare it in my Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and Experience to be <hi>moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent.</hi> And further that the moſt tender Conſtitutions need not dread it, provided it ſute their Maladies, for regularly uſed, it revives both the <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal</hi> and <hi>Natural</hi> Faculties, and in ſuch <hi>I</hi> have ever had the moſt ſtupendious Cures. Only let not ſuch adventure on it without very good advice, and daily Inſpection of ſome Phiſician at hand, in whom they may confide, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king it alſo at the Fountain.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> ſhall conclude with a ſtory that <hi>I</hi> meet with in <hi>Plutarchs;</hi> One <hi>Philippi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> an excellent Commedian had plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the King <hi>Lyſimachus</hi> very well, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o ſo much as the King asked <hi>Philip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pides,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:106770:80"/>Quid è meis Rebus tibi impertiam,</hi> What boon ſhall <hi>I</hi> give thee? He an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>Quidvis O Rex, Modo nequid Arcanorum,</hi> What you pleaſe, only tell me no Secrets.—<hi>I</hi> do ſtill profeſs my ſelf to be a Friend to <hi>Dr. Tunſtal,</hi> and am ready to make it out in any Civil Kindneſs, only (<hi>I</hi> hope) he will not henceforth expect that <hi>I</hi> tell him any Secret.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
